<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB_XML/main/Schema/FFDB_mini.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB_XML/main/Schema/FFDB_mini.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<body>
<head>NAF000373</head>
<p>Ddĭ̍-χérretẹn,<note>A man of the early race he was. His head was stone.</note> formerly, when the Lioness was at the water, dipping up,<note>I think that she probably dipped up water with a gemsbok's stomach; for she killed gemsbok.</note> [when] she had gone to dip <pb n="165"/>up water there, Ddĭ̍-χérretẹn felt that the Lioness was the one who had gathered together the people's children, because the Lioness felt that she was an invalid on account of [her] chest; therefore, she gathered together the people's children, that the children might live with her, that the children might work for her; for, she was an invalid, and she could not do hard work.</p>
<p>Therefore, Ddĭ̍-χérretẹn went to her house, when she was dipping up water. Ddĭ̍-χérretẹn went in her absence to the house, Ddĭ̍-χérretẹn went to the children, at the house. Ddĭ̍-χérretẹn went to the house reaching the children. Ddĭ̍-χérretẹn sat down. And Ddĭ̍-χérretẹn said: "O children sitting here! The fire of your people is that which is at the top of the ravine which comes down from the top [of the hill]" Therefore, two children arose, they went away to their own people.</p>
<p>Ddĭ̍-χérretẹn again said: "O children sitting here! The fire of your people is that which is below the top of the ravine which comes down on this side [of the hill]." And three children<note>Literally, "children which became three."</note> thus went, while they went away to their own people.</p>
<p>And he again said: "O little child sitting here! Thy people's fire is that which is below the top of the ravine which comes down on this side [of the hill]." And the child arose, it thus went, while the child went away to its own people.</p>
<p>He again said: "O children sitting here! The fire of your people is that which is below<note>Because the house is in the ravine [i.e., not where the water flows, but among the bushes].</note> the top <pb n="167"/>of the ravine<note>He speaks of another ravine.</note> which comes down on this side [of the hill]." And two children arose, they thus went away, while they went away to their own people.</p>
<p>And he again said: "O children sitting here! Your people's fire is that which is at the top. of the ravine which comes down from the top [of the hill]." And two children arose, they thus went away.</p>
<p>And he again said: "O children sitting here! The fire of your people is that which is at the top of the ravine which comes down from the top [of the hill]." And three children arose, they thus went away; while they went away to their own people.</p>
<p>And he again said: "O children sitting here!<note>Her children were not there; for the people's children were those whom she had.</note> The fire of your people is that which is at the top of the ravine which comes down from the top [of the hill]." And two children arose, they thus went away; while they went away to their own people; while Ddĭ̍-χérretẹn sat waiting for the Lioness.</p>
<p>And the Lioness came from the water, she thus returning came. She came along looking [at the house]; she did not perceive the children. And she exclaimed: "Why do the children [stammering with rage] children children children, the children not do so to me? and the children do not play here, as they are wont to do? It must be this man who sits at the house; his head resembles Ddĭ̍-χérretẹn."<note>She recognized him.</note></p>
<p>And she became angry about it, when she perceived <pb n="169"/>Ddĭ̍-χérretẹn.<note>Because she did not perceive the children.</note> She exclaimed: "Ddĭ̍-χérretẹn indeed [?] sits here!" She walked up to the house. She exclaimed: "Where are my children?"<note>The narrator's translation of ǀne ǀăuwaki ǃkaukẹn was "Where are my children?" but "Give me the children" or "Show me the children" may be verbally more accurate.</note> And Ddĭ̍-χérretẹn said: Our children [they] are not." And the Lioness exclaimed: "Out on thee! leave off! thou must give me the children!" Ddĭ̍-χérretẹn said: "Our children [they] were not."</p>
<p>And the Lioness caught hold of his head. She exclaimed: "χábbabbu"<note>Growling put in the head.</note> [growling] to the other one's head. And she exclaimed: "Oh! Oh dear! Oh dear! Oh dear! Oh dear! my teeth! This must be why this cursed [?] man's big head came to sit in front of my house!" While Ddĭ̍-χérretẹn said: "I told thee that our children they were not." The Lioness exclaimed: "Destruction! Thou hast been the one whose big head came to sit [here]." "Our children<note>Ddĭ̍-χérretẹn was the one who spoke thus.</note> [they] were not."</p>
<p>And he arose, he returned [home]; while the Lioness sat in anger at her house; because he had come [and] taken away from her the children, who had been [living] peacefully with her; for she felt that she had done well towards the children; she did not a little love the children while she was doing so.</p>
</body>