<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB_XML/main/Schema/FFDB_mini.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB_XML/main/Schema/FFDB_mini.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<body>
<head>NAF000471</head>
<p>We Bushmen do not have any cattle. We never had any cattle. A long time ago, we used to get cattle from the Bechuanas in this way. We would get on top of a high mountain, so that we could see well where the herds were with the cattle. We liked them to be far from the villages. We would look and see, and we would tell each other where the cattle were. A lot of us would go a long way. We would go silently, so that we would get round on one side of the Bechuanas. We knew they were much afraid of our poisoned arrows. Then some more of us would hide behind bushes and stones, or behind bits of grass, a little in front of the cattle. We would keep perfectly still until the others had got ready. Then when they were about to attack they would throw a handful of dust into the air. Then they would rise up and shout. They would fire some arrows at the herds. We on our side would lie quiet. The herds would say, "Au, Au," and they would rush at the Bushmen to chase them away, and we would rise and run round the cattle, and drive them off, while our friends would fight with the herds. In this way we would get away with a lot of cattle. We would drive them to our secret places in the mountains, where we would kill and eat them. We never kept them. Sometimes the Kafirs would pursue us. They would come because they were angry, and because they were many. Then sometimes we would have to leave the cattle and run away and save ourselves; but as soon as we saw the Bechuanas coming we always tried to kill as many of the cattle as possible, so that when the Bechuanas came they would not find any alive to drive away. Then when they had gone home, we would come down again and eat the meat; but sometimes the Bechuanas were too strong for us, and drove us off, killing some of us, or they would get our wives and children, and take them away. This is what I know of cattle stealing. It is the end of the tale.</p>
</body>