<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB_XML/main/Schema/FFDB_mini.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB_XML/main/Schema/FFDB_mini.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<body>
<head>NAF000342</head>
<p>When the moon died, it returned to life again, to pass again across the sky. "Everyone will do as I do," said the moon. "When a person has died, don't think that he will just die and lie there and rot. Take heed, follow what I, the moon do: I die and then live again, and die again only to live again. Everyone should do as I do."</p>
<p>But the <animal>hare</animal> contradicted the moon. "No!" he said. "A person is born and he must die also. When he rots he will smell bad."</p>
<p>The moon argued with him, and said "Watch me. I'm going to die and then I'll come alive again. Watch me and learn, and then we can both do it." But the <animal>hare</animal> refused. So the moon split his mouth open. The <animal>hare</animal> became the split-mouth <animal>hare</animal> that people chase.</p>
<p>The moon and the <animal>hare</animal> argued with each other and harangued each other. The moon said, "Take my advice ... a person will die and yet return." But the <animal>hare</animal> refused, so the moon took a hatchet and split his mouth. Then the <animal>hare</animal> scratched the moon's face in return. The two of them fought back and forth. The <animal>hare</animal> scratched the moon's face! That's why you can still see marks on the moon's face, because the <animal>hare</animal> scratched it and the scratches festered. When the <animal>hare</animal> had spoiled the moon's face, the two of them separated. They spent the next day separate, and the day after that. <epimyth>That's how their anger rose and they fought, chopping each others' mouths and clawing each others' faces.</epimyth></p>
</body>