<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB_XML/main/Schema/FFDB_mini.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB_XML/main/Schema/FFDB_mini.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<body>
<head>NAF000468</head>
<p>You know that we Bushmen are very much afraid of the lion. A long time ago we used to live in caves. We lived in them much more than we do now. That is how we became afraid of the lion. Some men and women were living in a. big cave near the Crocodile River. They had lived there for a long time, and the lions had never disturbed them, although the lions were many. The lions used to creep after their game, and they left the people alone. But one night, a very cold and wet night, a lion came to the mouth of the cave, and he began to shout, "I'm hungry, give me one of the children." The people were much afraid, and they kept very quiet; but as he kept on roaring, they began to throw burning sticks at him. He still kept on shouting, "Give me one of the children to eat." At last one man went out with a burning stick and threw it at the lion, to drive him away. But the lion growled at him, and when the man threw the burning stick at him he sprang upon it, and bit it, so that it went out. The lion kept on shouting, "I'm hungry, give me one of the children to eat." Another man went out with a burning stick to drive him away. The lion sprang at him, and he dropped the burning stick. The man was nearly caught by the teeth of the lion. The lion kept on roaring, but <pb n="83"/>he got nearer and nearer to the mouth of the cave, so that the people could see him plainly. The women and children were very much afraid, and kept pressing up against the back wall. Some of the men wanted to shoot with the bow a poisoned arrow at the lion, but the others said, "If you do so, he will leap into the cave and catch us all." The lion then came right into the cave, and he shouted as before, "I'm hungry, give me one of the children to eat." The fire in the cave was beginning to burn low, as the people were very much afraid to blow it up. Now a man stood up, and seizing a child, flung it to the lion, saying, "There, father, there is meat." The lion caught the child in his teeth. The people were able to escape on both sides of him, and no more of them were eaten. From that day we don't like to live in caves. We build our huts in the open, where if a lion comes we can very easily run away in the darkness, and escape into the bushes. This is the end of the tale.</p>
</body>