<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB_XML/main/Schema/FFDB_mini.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB_XML/main/Schema/FFDB_mini.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<body>
<head>NAF000331</head>
<p>The kori bustard was very fat. Fat hung under his armpits and that was how he fed the fire he kept hidden there. The kori bustard was the first animal to have fire.</p>
<p>One day ǃGara found a big ball of edible gum high in a tree. He said to the kori bustard, "Stretch out your wing and point to the gum for me so I can climb up and get it." When the kori bustard stretched out his wing, ǃGara noticed that smoke was coming from under his armpits. He saw the fat hanging there. He grabbed it and went home. He cooked it and ate it. Everyone went to sleep.</p>
<p>In the morning, ǃGara said to the kori bustard, "A few days ago I saw a lot of gum off in that direction. I poked a large ball of it down from a tree but it got lost in the bushes. I looked for it but couldn't find it. Let's go together and get it."</p>
<p>So they walked to where the gum was. When they had located it, ǃGara said, "Let's race each other for it!" Both of them scrambled towards the gum. The kori bustard jumped and grabbed it. Then ǃGara grabbed the kori bustard and took him home with the intention of cooking him.</p>
<p>Back in his camp he boiled the kori bustard and began to drink his fat. His fat flanks, his stomach, his fat wings - ǃGara ate them all. Then he took the path out of camp and went and had diarrhea in the bushes. While he was gone, the remains of the kori bustard began jumping up and down in the pot. ǃGara ran back to see what was going on. But then he had to run back to the bushes again to defecate some more. Then he hurried to the pot to see whether the kori bustard was still in it.</p>
<p>All the while he was running back and forth, the kori bustard was jumping up and down in the pot. At last, he got out and began to escape. ǃGara ran after him, but the others said, "Come back and get something to hit him with! Come back and get a knobkerrie, come back and get a knobkerrie!" ǃGara ran back as they told him, and the kori bustard took off in the opposite direction. ǃGara threw the knobkerrie after him, but the kori bustard flew away. ǃGara was left jumping up and down on the ground.</p>
</body>