<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB_XML/main/Schema/FFDB_mini.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB_XML/main/Schema/FFDB_mini.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<body>
<head>NAF000470</head>
<p>The honey bird is a small bird, and flies about trying to tell the Bushmen where the bees have their nests. Now the Bushmen are very fond of the honey of the bees, and sometimes they will climb very high rocks to get at the honey. One day a Bushman had been out hunting, and he killed nothing. He went to sleep under a small tree. A honey bird came and waked him up by calling out, "Come, I will take you where there is a large bees' nest." The Bushman knew that the honey bird always found the bees' nests, and as he was hungry he followed the bird. It led him a very long distance, and he was beginning to get tired, when they came to <pb n="84"/>the bottom of a very high cliff. There it stopped, and the Bushman began to gaze up at the face of the cliff to find out where the bees were coming out and in. The honey bird was sitting on a branch near by, saying, "You will give me some of the comb." But a lion was watching that Bushman from behind a small bush at the bottom of the cliff, and the man did not see him. Just as the lion was shaking his loins before springing on the man, the Bushman saw him. He turned and ran, and the lion sprang, after him. The lion nearly caught him, but the man threw away his bow, his quiver, and his kaross just as the lion overtook him. The lion stopped, growled, and began to tear up the kaross. So the man escaped. That is why we Bushmen are very careful when following the honey bird, and when it stops, we always stand back a bit, and have a look round the place before we venture forward, for fear there might be a lion. That is the whole of the tale.</p>
</body>