<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB_XML/main/Schema/FFDB_mini.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB_XML/main/Schema/FFDB_mini.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<body>
<head>NAF002030</head>
<p>First there were people as we are now.</p>
<p>And the men left the women at home and went to hunt eland. And they go and they kill the elands.</p>
<p>When they are about to return, one of the children started to cry. He cried and cried and cried and they couldn't get him to stop. And the women then asked each other what they could do. They want to stop him, stop him. Stop him! Stop! And he just doesn't listen; he just ignores them. And they tried and tried and they asked the others, "What can we do?"</p>
<p>And they take a blanket [antelope skin kaross] and wrap it into the trunk of an elephant. And they take another two blankets and shape them into the ears of an elephant. In the old time they had big plates on which to save their [left-over?] food. And they take two of those dishes and put the child's feet on them.</p>
<p>And he starts walking and pulling the trees down, just breaking the trees.</p>
<p>And the women, when they see the boy's doing this, they say "eh, hem" and they start doing the same thing as the boy. And they followed the boy. And then they pull the trees down, like the boy, and then they follow him and again pull down the trees.</p>
<p><pb n="373"/>When the sun is about to set the men who were hunting came back. When they came they found an old woman staying alone at home. And they asked her, "Where are the others?" And the old woman told them, "Just look at those trees all over the ground; those trees were broken by the people".</p>
<p>And then those men, who had just come from hunting, they just threw the meat on the ground and started to do what the women and the boy were doing. And then they left the old woman with that meat. And they followed them.</p>
<p>And the old woman started to eat that meat, and eat it, and eat it, and eat it. When the meat is finished she started to wrap the blankets and make ears and a trunk and place big dishes on her feet. And she followed them.</p>
<p>And she followed them and met up with them and she started cutting down the trees and pull down the trees.</p>
<p>And they eat the trees, some of them pull down some more trees and eat some of them. They eat it and break it, and eat it and break it and eat it and break it.</p>
<p>And where they had lived first, when they were people, those trees were very beautiful and tall trees. They were living at a nice place where there is a big boulder lying on the ground beside the trees. And it is at these large stones where the people had lived at first.</p>
<p><epimyth>This is a story I heard from the oldest people.</epimyth></p>
</body>