<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB_XML/main/Schema/FFDB_mini.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB_XML/main/Schema/FFDB_mini.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<body>
<head>NAF000328</head>
<p>Yes, I know: certainly I know what the springhare and ǁaiha did.</p>
<p>ǁaiha, you know, made everything, all by himself. And he had a beautiful loincloth. They had sewn beads on it for him: it was beautiful all over. He liked to put it on and dance with it, dance with it to the dancing songs.</p>
<p>One day he was out walking in his loincloth. He came to where the springhare was. The springhare took a look at the loincloth and said "What's that beautiful thing you've got. Lend it to me: let me try it on. Won't you let me try it out? Give it to me so I can dance in it."</p>
<p>So ǁaiha took off the loincloth. He gave it to the springhare to try on. The springhare tied it around his waist and began to dance with it. He danced and danced. He began to look really good. The little loincloth looked beautiful as it bobbed up and down. ǁaiha was entranced by the sight. He stayed there and watched the springhare dance. He watched and watched. The springhare danced and ǁaiha watched him. Neither one of them realized that rainclouds were gathering and coming toward them.</p>
<p>When the rain was almost upon them, ǁaiha said "Hey, springhare! Give me my loincloth so I can go home. You can see that it's about to rain." But the springhare paid him no mind, and just went on dancing. He danced and danced. Again ǁaiha said "Hey! Springhare! Give me back my loincloth - I'm going home! It's going to rain!" But the springhare refused and just kept dancing. He danced here and he danced there, and then the rain was upon them. ǁaiha jumped up and said "What am I going to do with this guy? I've told him to give me my loincloth, I've told him it's about to rain, but he just goes on dancing!" He ran at the springhare and tried to grab him. He chased him and chased him. Finally he was close enough to get his hands on him, but just then the springhare popped into his hole. He got away, loincloth and all.</p>
<p>There was nothing for ǁaiha to do but go home. He threw up his hands in disgust and walked off. The beautiful loincloth became the springhare's tail. Ever since then the springhare goes about with this tail, a tail that once was ǁaiha's loincloth. That's how the story goes.</p>
</body>