<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB_XML/main/Schema/FFDB_mini.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB_XML/main/Schema/FFDB_mini.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<body>
<head>NAF000327</head>
<p>Kauha and ǃõǃõtsiǀdasi ["Eyes on His Ankles"] went digging ǁxaru. They dug and dug and then they slept. While ǃõǃõtsiǀdasi was asleep, Kauha looked at him and wondered where his eyes were, because he could not see any on his face. "Where can this guy's eyes be?" Kauha felt all over him, searching around for his eyes. But no matter where he touched, no eyelids blinked. "Where does he keep his eyes?" Next Kauha touched ǃõǃõtsiǀdasi's wrists, but nothing blinked there. "Where can his eyes be?" All this time, ǃõǃõtsiǀdasi was fast asleep. Kauha had worked his way down to his ankles, and he threw a little sand on them. Suddenly, something blinked! "Hai?" said Kauha. "Is this where he keeps his eyes?" He flicked sand on the other ankle. When this ankle blinked too, Kauha asked again, "Have his eyes been on his ankles all along?"</p>
<p>Kauha and ǃõǃõtsiǀdasi were the first to play the game of "War." ǃõǃõtsiǀdasi won continually. He won and won, because Kauha didn't know where his eyes were. That's why he was looking for ǃõǃõtsiǀdasi's eyes by flicking sand on them. "Just wait: I'll fix you," Kauha thought to himself. So he searched and searched until he found his eyes. Then he said to ǃõǃõtsiǀdasi, "Let's go dig ǁxaru." So they dug and dug. Then they came home and built a fire to roast what they had dug. The fire burned and burned until it settled into coals. Kauha refused that ǃõǃõtsiǀdasi put the ǁxaru into the coals - he did it himself. He dropped one ǁxaru after another into the coals. Suddenly he grabbed ǃõǃõtsiǀdasi and thrust him into the coals with the ǁxaru! He raked the embers over him with the fire paddle. ǃõǃõtsiǀdasi's eyes were burned. Kahua roasted them together with the ǁxaru. The ǁxaru sat in the fire and cooked until it was done, Kauha raked it out and set it aside to cool. Then he filled his bag with it and went off, leaving ǃõǃõtsiǀdasi to nurse his burned eyes.</p>
</body>