<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB_XML/main/Schema/FFDB_mini.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB_XML/main/Schema/FFDB_mini.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<body>
<head>NEE023317</head>
<p><note>This and the legend "Siamang Child" have many common features. It is possible that they have become mixed up.</note></p>
<p>There was once a girl who lived alone in a house built on top of an old grave. She did not know that there was a grave underneath her house. Her mother lived elsewhere; she did not want to live with her daughter. One day the girl went fishing, and she caught several river Crabs. These she brought home and ate. She became pregnant from having eaten the crabs. This would not have happened had she not lived on top of a grave. Everybody said that she had been made pregnant by her older brother. He lived in a different settlement, and when he heard that his sister was pregnant, he went to help her. He made her a proper new house and cleared a field for her. He suffered very badly from a skin disease, and when he went bathing in the river and washed his body, the poison from the skin disease killed all the fish around, so he brought back a lot of fish for his sister. After a while the child was born, but it was not a human being, it was a crab. The brother then returned to his own house, but after a few years he came to visit his sister. The crab child wanted to climb on his uncle's knees, but he was frightened of the claws, and asked the crab to stay on the ground.</p>
<p>Later the girl married Bongso Pinto Tam.<note>His name means 'opening (of) river,' in other words 'the headwaters of a river'. This indicates that Bongso came from such a place. The people who live at the headwaters of the rivers are bi inhar</note> He was a petri.<note>Petri is probably derived from the Malay puteri meaning 'princess'. In Chewong usage the word petri always refers to a special kind of superhuman being. They look just like ordinary people, but they have cool eyes, and they live in unusual places, such as the headwaters of a river, or inside a large stone. Their characteristic feature, however, is the fact that they were "born alone". This means that they do not have parents, but made themselves. I was unable to obtain any further details.</note> When the crab child was grown up he wanted a wife. His mother went in search of a wife for him. She brought with her a sarong to a house and told her errand. "No, we don't want a crab husband!" cried the young girls who lived there, and threw ash at her. The mother went home and told her son what had happened. "Try the house over there," said he, and the next day the mother went. But the girls did not want him either, and they also threw ash at her. So she went home and the son asked her to try yet another house. She went the next day, and the young girl who lived there said that she wanted to marry the crab. They prepared the wedding, and they cooked rice in the crab's house as well as in the girl's house. Everyone went to eat at the crab's house. When they had finished they moved to the girl's house. On the way the crab became a real human being. He was very handsome and when he arrived at his wife's house all the young girls looked at him, and those who had thrown ashes at his mother were very ashamed.</p>
</body>