<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB_XML/main/Schema/FFDB_mini.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB_XML/main/Schema/FFDB_mini.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<body>
<head>NEE023336</head>
<p>A long time ago there were no dogs. Two sisters lived together with their husbands. One day the two brothers-in-law went hunting with their blowpipes. They came across a boweig monkey which they shot. It fell dead on the ground. The two men left it on a stone and walked on. They met a tobowad monkey which they also shot. This they brought back to the place where they had left the boweig monkey, and they made a fire in order to eat some of the meat. One of the men removed the animal stomachs and intestines and placed them on a leaf. He then wiped the blood off the carcases with another leaf. The other man watched him and asked, "Do you want to eat that, brother-in-law?" "No, to do so is dirty (<ref target="g:GEE2143.019">kama</ref>)," replied the first man. They cooked some of the meat and ate it. Then they put the rest in their back-baskets and set off home. Halfway, the second man exclaimed, "Oh brother-in-law!" "What is it, brother-in-law?" asked the first man. "I have left my knife behind," he replied, but in fact he had hidden it in his join cloth. "You had better return to look for it, brother-in-law," the first man told him. The man went back to where they had cooked the monkeys and here he ate all the intestines and licked the leave which were with the blood. The other man returned home and gave the monkeys to his wife to cook. She cooked the meat and she cooked some tubers. "Your husband is very late," she told her sister. Finally the man arrived saying that he had not found his knife at first as it was hidden underneath some leaves. Everybody ate and then went to sleep.</p>
<p>For the next four days the same thing happened, except that each time the man gave a different reason for being late back. Once he said that his knife had fallen behind a stone, another time that there were lots of mosquitoes which made searching difficult, that the knife had fallen into the river, and finally, that he had forgotten where he left it.</p>
<p>Then the younger brother of the first man joined the two men on the hunt. When the man said that he had forgotten his knife and went back to look for it, his brother-in-law said to his younger brother, "You go home with the meat. I want to follow after brother-in-law to see what he does." He went after the man and saw how he returned to the spot where they had gutted the animals caught that day. He watched how he ate the intestines and licked the blood. Then he went home and told the rest what he had seen.</p>
<p>When the man who had eaten the stomach contents returned home, his wife was angry with him for being late. "I met a tiger which was eating a pig it had killed, and it followed after me," he lied. The wife then told him what her sister's husband had seen. The husband and wife quarrelled. The man hit his wife and killed her. He then bit off a piece of her flesh and ate it.</p>
<p>The next day the father of the two sisters arrived at their house. He knew what had happened. He was a great <ref target="g:GEE2143.032">putao</ref>. He took the corpse of his daughter and touched it on the shins, toes, and head. Then he blew 'magical smoke' (<ref target="g:GEE2143.027">òz taba</ref>) over it seven times. The woman became alive again. Her father then took his <pb n="75"/>spear and struck his son-in-law in the chest. The son-in-law died. The father placed the corpse inside the house and set fire to it. The corpse of the son-in-law became ashes, and the man took these and threw them in all directions. They turned into all the different kinds of dogs that exist today, black dogs, white dogs, brown dogs, and spotted dogs.</p>
<p>The man who was eating the intestines and licking the blood was in fact becoming a dog. He was no longer a true human being. He behaved as dogs do by eating the dirty parts of game.</p>
</body>