<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB_XML/main/Schema/FFDB_mini.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB_XML/main/Schema/FFDB_mini.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<body>
<head>NEE023319</head>
<p>Yaʼ Popag, who was a nʼlab [bas who eat people's bodies as opposed to their <ref target="g:GEE2143.036">ruwai</ref>] lived alone in her house in a large field where she had planted lots of rice. A man from another settlement went out hunting one day and he passed Yaʼ Popag's house. "Come over here, grandchild, rest a little," she called out to him. He entered her house. Yaʼ Popag cooked rice and gave him to eat. After they had eaten, they smoked and Yaʼ Popag gave him some betel nuts to chew. These betel nuts, however, were poisonous and the man fell asleep. He lay flat on his back. Yaʼ Popag went up to him and asked, "Are you asleep, grand child?" He did not reply. She then took her knife and slit his throat. She drank his blood and ate his body. Then she took his blowpipe, his quiver, and the bones, and brought them over to the house of a young girl nearby. Yaʼ Popag had already eaten the girl's mother, but the girl herself - she was Bongso [and therefore <ref target="g:GEE2143.032">putao</ref>] - made herself very, very small so that Yaʼ Popag did not want to eat her. She thought there would be no blood in her and no meat on her bones. The girl was tiny in the daytime when she might be visited by Yaʼ Popag. In the evenings she became normal again.</p>
<p>The man's brother went hunting as well. He also came acrosss Yaʼ Popag's house, and she called out to him to enter her house and have a rest. When they had eaten she gave him some of the poisonous betel nut and when he fell asleep she cut his throat, drank his blood, and ate his body. Then she placed his blowpipe, quiver, and bones in the young girl's house. After a few days yet another brother came to Yaʼ Popag's house, and the same thing happened.</p>
<p>The following day Bongso went out looking for his brother He arrived at the house of the young girl. There he saw his brothers' blowpipes and quivers. "Yaʼ Popag has eaten all your brothers," the girl told him. He then walked over to Yaʼ Popag's house. "Is that you, my grandchild?" she called out when she saw him. "It is I, Granny," he replied. "Come in and rest a little and have something to eat," she said. "No, I am staying over there," he replied, pointing towards the girl's house. He did not want to eat human flesh. To do so would be dirty (<ref target="g:GEE2143.019">kama</ref>). The following morning he returned to Yaʼ Popag's house. "Let us go and harvest your rice, Granny", he said, "I can see that it is ripe." "Not today, grandchild, it is too hot. Come inside the house for a bit," she answered. "No, come on," he insisted, "grandmother and grandchild working together won't notice the heat." So they went. As the sun got higher in the sky, Yaʼ Popag complained of the heat. "Let us go home, grandchild," she said. "No, no, Granny, when grandmother and her grandchild work together they don't notice the heat," he replied. They worked on and it was very hot. Every so often Yaʼ Popag wanted to go home, but Bongso would not let her. She did not want to oppose him as she intended to kill and eat him later. When the sun began to set, Bongso said, "Let us go bathing, Granny." They went to the river, but by this time it was almost evening, and Yaʼ Popag said, "it is too cold to bathe now, grandchild." "No, it is not. In you go," he told her. She jumped in. "Oh, it is cold!" she exclaimed and wanted to get out <pb n="64"/>straight away. "No, not yet Granny," said Bongso, "stay in a bit longer. You will feel very good afterwards." When Yaʼ Popag finally was allowed to get out of the water she was shivering with cold. "I'll run on ahead and build you a fire so that you can warm yourself," Bongso told her. He made a large fire on the ground underneath the ladder leading up to Yaʼ Popag's house, and when she arrived she leant against the ladder to warm herself. She was shivering. After a while Bongso told her to enter the house. She started climbing up the ladder. She had to do it on all fours. She was so exhausted after the day's work and her trials. When she was halfway up, the ladder collapsed into the fire and Yaʼ Popag was burned to death.</p>
<p>Bongso then went over to the girl's house. He took the bones of his three brothers and washed them. Then he laid them out on the ground and blew magical smoke (<ref target="g:GEE2143.027">òz taba</ref>) over them and on top of their heads. Three times he did this and they became alive again. "Oh, dear, we have been sleeping in the day time," they exclaimed, "it was very nice." "Nice indeed!" replied Bongso, "you have been killed and eaten by Yaʼ Popag." He then told them all that had happened. In the night Bongso and the girl slept together and they became husband and wife. The next day they all returned to their mother's house. "You have been out hunting for a long time," said she when she saw them. "No, they were killed and eaten by Yaʼ Popag," said Bongso, "I took their bones and made them alive again. "Oh," said the mother, "where is Yaʼ Popag now?" "I have killed her with fire," Bongso told her.</p>
<p>After a few days, when the three brothers were strong again, they all returned to Yaʼ Popag's field. They did not want all the rice that was still there to be abandoned. They threw away the roof, floor, and beams of her house and built a new one for themselves to live in.</p>
</body>