<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB_XML/main/Schema/FFDB_mini.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB_XML/main/Schema/FFDB_mini.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<body>
<head>NEE023339</head>
<p>Once there was a brother and sister whose parents had died. The girl was an adolescent and the boy could only just walk. The sister was very fond of her little brother, and when their parents died she carried her brother and went into the jungle looking for people. After a while they met a man. He wanted to marry the girl, but he did not want to look after the little boy, so he built a house on stilts high off the ground and with no openings. He placed the child inside the house and left him there, taking with him the girl.</p>
<p>The child cried and cried. A tiger heard the crying and went to investigate. He could smell that there was a person inside the house and he tried to get in. He clawed at the walls, but he could not break through, so he went down to the area underneath the house and went to sleep. The child was not big enough to be frightened of tigers. He wanted to go and play with it, but he could not get out.</p>
<p>A few days later Bongso was walking in the jungle. He heard the crying. "There are people around somewhere here," he said to himself and went in search of them. He came to the house in the trees and realized that the crying came from there. Then he saw the tiger asleep underneath. Bongso killed the tiger with his spear and climbed up to the house. He took the boy and brought him to his own house where the boy lived together with Bongso from then on.</p>
<p>The years passed, and when the boy was a youth, there was a feast in Bongso's settlement and people came from all the other settlements to take part. The boy's sister also came with her husband. She saw her younger brother, but she did not recognize him. When they had eaten, the boy went up to his sister and asked her who she was and why she looked so sad. "Oh, I live over there with my husband," she said. "I once had a small brother. Our parents died and I was carrying him through the jungle when we met my husband. My husband did not want my brother so he built a house in a tree and left my brother inside it. I was very fond of my little brother and I miss him very much. A tiger is sure to have eaten him." "Oh," said the boy, "that was me. Bongso found me in a house with no openings, in the jungle. There was a tiger underneath the house wanting to eat me, but Bongso killed it and brought me to his own house where I have lived ever since." When she heard this the girl was very angry with her husband, and he left and went home alone. The girl married Bongso.</p>
</body>