<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB_XML/main/Schema/FFDB_mini.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB_XML/main/Schema/FFDB_mini.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<body>
<head>NEE023331</head>
<p>A man went hunting with his blowpipe. He shot a tobowad monkey which he placed in his backbasket. Then he found some pre fruit. These he put in his tobacco pouch and pushed it down the front of his loincloth. He returned home to the swidden where he gave the tobowad to his two wives [who were sisters] and his parents-in-law, but he did not tell them he had found any pre fruit. They all ate the meat with <plant latin="manihot utilissima">tapioca</plant> and rice and the parents-in-law went to sleep immediately afterwards. The man shared his fruit with his wives and the three of the them ate it alone.<note>To keep desirable food away from somebody i.e. not to share it is tiger <ref target="g:GEE2143.030">punén</ref> and usually (but not in this legend) it causes the person offended against to be attacked by a tiger.</note> He did not give any to his parents-in-law.</p>
<p>The next day he went hunting again. He returned to the same spot where he had shot the tobowad monkey the day before. Here he shot another one. Then he went to the pre fruit tree and made lots fall down with a long stick. Again he put the fruit in his tobacco pouch which he pushed down the front of his loincloth. He went home, gave the tobowad to his wives and mother-in-law and told them "I cannot find any pre fruit." The women cooked the meat which they all ate. The parents-in-law went to sleep and the man shared the pre fruit with his wives only.</p>
<p>A few days later the man and his two wives went on a hunting expedition. They made a lean-to on the ground, and were going to spend a few nights in the jungle. The husband went off with his blowpipe while the wives stayed behind. He shot a squirrel. It fell to the ground and he wrapped it with leaves, hali klawòden. As he bent over to place the wrapped meat in his back-basket a tiger came upon him from behind and bit him in the neck.<note>It will be remembered that to wrap meat in klawòden leaves is tiger <ref target="g:GEE2143.041">talaiden</ref>. In this story, the man commits two different offences. It is possible that two stories have become mixed into one.</note></p>
<p>The tiger took the man's tobacco pouch and went to the lean-to where the wives were waiting for their husband to return. The tiger threw the tobacco pouch from a distance. There was some blood on it. "What is this blood?" asked the wives. "It is some blood from a boweig monkey," replied the tiger. The wives could not see the tiger, they thought it was their husband speaking. Then the tiger went and collected the man's blowpipe and quiver. He threw the blowpipe to the wives. It broke. He also threw the quiver which split open. There was some blood on the quiver. "What is this blood?" asked the wives, "That is blood from a boweig monkey," replied the tiger. The tiger went to the dead man and bit off his penis, brought it back to the wives and threw it to them from a distance. "Whose penis is that?" the wives wanted to know. "That is the boweig monkey's penis," replied the tiger. He went and tore out the man's stomach and threw that as well. The wives now realized that a tiger had killed their husband and they ran to a tall tree and climbed up it.</p>
<p>In the morning the wives heard siamang chatter in the distance. They also <pb n="85"/>heard gibbons and boweig monkeys. "l am going hunting," said the tiger, still pretending to be the husband, "I'll be back in the evening." The tiger went off in the direction of where they heard the siamang, gibbon and boweig monkey. The wives climbed down from the tree and ran as fast as they could towards the swidden. They stumbled and fell. When the older sister fell the younger one stepped over her, and when the younger sister fell the elder stepped over her. When they reached the swidden they told their mother, "A tiger has killed our husband." They explained how they had committed <ref target="g:GEE2143.030">punén</ref> by not sharing the pre fruit. They all ate and then went to sleep.</p>
<p>The next day the father-in-law built a spear-trap on the path to the swidden. In the night the tiger came but the spears did not hit him. He killed a domestic pig, but only ate the blood. The following day the father-in-law built a trap right next to the ladder leading up to the house. He dug a hole in the ground and placed many spears at the bottom of the pit with the pointed ends upwards. He covered it with leaves. In the night the tiger came, carrying the corpse of the husband in his mouth. He carried him by the neck where he had first bitten him. The tiger fell into the prepared trap, on top of all the spears, and the father-in-law came out of the house where he had been waiting, and finished him off.</p>
<p>The next day they buried the two corpses. The tiger was buried on one side of a tree, the man on the other side.<note>Tigers would not usually be buried; the only animals so disposed of are dogs, "because they are our friends." No one could offer an explanation why it was buried on this occasion, but they were insistent that the two corpses had to be kept apart by the tree, otherwise the "yinlugen would not go to their own afterworlds, but might go to the wrong ones.</note></p>
</body>