<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB_XML/main/Schema/FFDB_mini.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB_XML/main/Schema/FFDB_mini.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<body>
<head>NEE023302</head>
<p>A monitor-lizard man lived with his aunt (<ref target="g:GEE2143.003">baha</ref>). One day he asked her, "Take these things and go to the house over there and see if you can find a wife for me!" The aunt went and when she reached the house she was asked to step inside. She was given rice to eat and then they ate betel nuts. When they had finished eating the aunt put the things - rings, sarongs, bracelets and earrings - on the floor. "What is this, aunt?" asked the girls' mother. "Well, the monitor lizard wants a wife," replied the aunt. "I don't know", replied the mother, "it is really up to the girls." "No, we do not want to. How can you sleep with a monitor lizard" they said, so the aunt went home. The next day the monitor lizard asked her to take the things and go to another house. She was welcomed by the people there, given tobacco, rice and betel nuts; but when she placed the things she brought with her on the floor and asked if any of the girls wanted the monitor lizard for husband, they all said no. The monitor lizard asked his aunt to try several other houses, but in all cases the answer was the same, until one day she entered a house where the daughter put on all the things that the aunt had brought with her. When the aunt came home she told the monitor lizard that the girl had taken all the things. "But" she said, "she does not want you!" In the evening, however, the girl arrived and said that she was to become the monitor lizard's wife. She slept at one end of the house and he slept at the other end. In the morning all the girls who had refused him came to have a look at the couple.</p>
<p>The next day there was a feast in a nearby settlement. "You go," said the monitor lizard to his wife. "I'll stay at home." She went. As she sat down to eat, a handsome young man arrived and sat next to her. He ate out of her plate, and later helped himself to betel nuts from her pouch. It was the monitor lizard who had taken off his monitor lizard "cloak" (<ref target="g:GEE2143.004">bajo</ref> challag) and walked a different path to the house; but his wife did not know this nor did anyone else. All the girls were looking at him. When they had finished eating they all went home, but the monitor lizard man ran ahead, and by the time his wife reached their house he had put on his lizard cloak again. "A very handsome young man sat next to me at the feast," the girl told her monitor lizard husband, "he ate out of my plate, smoked my tobacco and helped himself to my betel nuts." "Ah, that was your husband," said the monitor lizard. "Nonsense," replied the girl.</p>
<p>A few days later there was another feast in another house and everyone went. The wife also went, but the monitor lizard said he wanted to stay at home. When the girl sat down to eat, the handsome man from the last feast sat next to her, and as on the last occasion, he ate out of her plate, smoked her tobacco and ate her betel nuts. "He must be a <ref target="g:GEE2143.033">raja</ref>," said all the girls present. He was handsome and they could not keep their eyes off him. When they had finished eating they all returned home, but the monitor lizard man ran ahead and by the time his wife arrived he had put on his monitor lizard cloak again and pretended to be asleep. The girl told him that the same young man had been present at the feast and that <pb n="22"/>he had eaten out of her plate, smoked her tobacco and taken her betel nuts. "That is your husband," the monitor lizard told her, but his wife became angry at hearing this.</p>
<p>Some time later there was yet another feast. This time the wife pretended to go to it, but she hid behind some banana trees close to the house and waited. She saw the same handsome man leave her house as had been sitting next to her at the other feasts. When he had walked past, she ran back to the house. She found the lizard skin lying there. She tore it into shreds and waited. When the monitor lizard man arrived at the feast and saw that his wife was not there, he returned home. He looked fir his lizard cloak, but could find it nowhere. "Where is my cloak, my original cloak?" he cried. "I have torn it up," his wife told him. "You must become a real human being and a real husband." So they slept together.</p>
<p>When the other girls saw that the man from the previous feasts was the girl's husband, they becarne very ashamed to think that they had refused him.</p>
</body>