<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB_XML/main/Schema/FFDB_mini.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB_XML/main/Schema/FFDB_mini.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<body>
<head>NEE023308</head>
<p>In the old days <animal>Tiger</animal> did not eat human beings. She would go to places where people lived and take a small child and bring it to her own house where she would look after it and rear it. When the child became old it would return to its mother and father, and <animal>Tiger</animal> would take another small child instead and bring it up. Each time the child had grown up, however, <animal>Tiger</animal> would let it go home. People did not mind letting <animal>Tiger</animal> have the children, they knew that she would look after them well.</p>
<p>Then one day as <animal>Tiger</animal> was carrying a new child back to her house, she met a <animal>toad</animal> who asked her what she was doing. "I am bringing my new child home," replied <animal>Tiger</animal>. "That is not your child, that is our meat (<ref target="g:GEE2143.002">ai</ref>)" said the <animal>toad</animal>. "No, no," said <animal>Tiger</animal>, "It is my child. I look after it." "It is very good to eat," the <animal>toad</animal> told her, "We'll eat it together". "No, no, it is my child," insisted <animal>Tiger</animal>. But the <animal>toad</animal> took the child and struck it so hard that it died. Then she cut it up into little pieces, put them in a <plant>bamboo</plant> and cooked it. When it was cooked she gave some meat to the <animal>tiger</animal>. "Try a little, it is very good," she told the <animal>tiger</animal> who then tasted just a tiny bit. "Oh, it is very good!" exclaimed <animal>Tiger</animal>, and together the <animal>toad</animal> and <animal>Tiger</animal> finished eating the child. Once having got the taste for human flesh, <animal>Tiger</animal> wanted more, and she killed and ate the next human child she took. When people found out that <animal>Tiger</animal> was eating their children, they no longer gave away their children to her. <epimyth>From then on <animal>tigers</animal> have been hunting humans.</epimyth></p>
</body>