<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB_XML/main/Schema/FFDB_mini.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB_XML/main/Schema/FFDB_mini.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<body>
<head>NEE028167</head>
<p>I was a wealthy man. I being a wealthy man, there was <pb n="194"/>a river on my estate. [There] being that river, [there] were many fishes [in it] every year. [There] being many fishes, I fished [for them]. When I had caught [them], I dried [them]. Drying [them], [and] killing many fishes, I had dried fish. Having dried fish, I had six storehouses full [of them]. [I] having [these six], from all places did wealthy people come to buy food of me.</p>
<p>When they came, various precious things and various swords did they barter for food. Yearly doing [this], I lived [as] a most wealthy man. Doing [so], [it happened] one year [that there] was not a single fish in the river of my estate. As there were none, [yet] was [there] food in the six storehouses from the year before. [There] being [food] from the year before, though my estate had abounded in fish every season, [yet] since [there] were now no fishes, all the food in the six storehouses was [at last] exhausted. Being exhausted, to eat had I nothing.</p>
<p>Therefore one day I went to my lake to angle. Having gone, I angled. I angling, not a fish bit. None <pb n="195"/>doing [so], I could no longer angle. [It] being thus, when I thought to go back, [there] was the noise of a fish biting. Therefore joyfully I pulled the hook [up]. When I had pulled the hook up, that fish said:</p>
<p>"Pull me quickly, pull me fast!" so it said. Therefore then I pulled quickly. When I had pulled quickly: "Pull me quickly, pull me fast!" so [it] said once more. Therefore, pulling quickly, I drew [it] to the edge of the ice-hole. Having pulled it out, I struck it on the head. When I had struck it on the head, that fish said":</p>
<p>" E ... Rich man of Otasta, strike me quickly on the head, strike me fast on the head. Eat me quickly, eat me fast!" Thus [it] spoke. Therefore knocking it quickly on the head, I killed [it]. When I had killed the fish, [it] said: " E ... Rich man of Otasta, quickly squeeze me, squeeze me fast! Quickly eat me, eat me fast!" So [it] said. When I looked, [I saw] it was a real silverfish.</p>
<p>When I reflected, I then thought it was not indeed a fish. Now being without food, having come to the lake by <pb n="196"/>the top of the bank of my river which gave me food every season, - being [thus] without food, being hungry, and having come to look [for] something to eat ... now was [it] a fish? or a god that jesting, did thus, [and] having transformed himself into a fish, ordered me to draw him out?</p>
<p>Thinking thus, - was not [this] an evil god? - thus thinking, having drawn out a dagger with a bone-inlaid hilt, I cut up the fish. When I cut up the fish, [it] spoke thus: "E ... Rich man of Otasta, cut me up quickly, cut me up fast. Squeeze me quickly, squeeze me fast. Eat me quickly, eat me fast". So I cut it up quickly, in pieces I cut [it].</p>
<p>Having cut it up, I gave it to the trees, and to the birds, and to every [sort of] grass. Having done, I went home. Having gone, I fell asleep at night. Sleeping. I had a dream. The dream was as follows. "Now, man of Otasta, hitherto thy estate has been an estate so abundant in fish. <pb n="197"/>It being so, this year being a year, there is not one single fish; thou thyself art not guilty that [there] are no fish.</p>
<p>I am the god of famine. Being so, I have, on purpose [and] in jest, not shown a single fish. So then, going yesterday to angle in thy lake, thou didst this not of thyself. I sent thee. I sent thee, and yesterday, though thou didst angle, yet couldst thou [catch] nothing. Now, when about to end [this jest], I let myself be caught by thee.</p>
<p>I am no true fish; the god of famine am I. Being the god of famine, on purpose, wishing to see thy intelligence, transformed into a fish, I let myself be pulled out. Thereafter, had understanding not been in thee [and] hadst thou eaten, thou wouldst have died. However, indeed, the guardian [spirit] of the rich man of Otasta being mighty, now thou hast not eaten me. So now thou hast destroyed me utterly.</p>
<p>Having done [this], to-morrow when thou risest. naming the god of famine, [and] when thou raisest an 'inau', then thou wilt see". Such [words in] a dream, I heard. The <pb n="198"/>next day I rose. Having risen I reflected: Really some god. jesting with me, has done this. Thus I remained in thought. Thus I thought, and likewise [that] the dream had been given me by that god.</p>
<p>Such being [the case], after the dream, trusting to [this] dream, made I an 'inau'. Naming the god of famine, made I [that] 'inau'. Afterwards I lived [as usual]. I living [thus], the god of famine had been really abashed [by me] in my turn; again my estate was abundant in fish; more fish were [there] than every season there had been. When there was much fish, catching I dried them.</p>
<p>The storehouses for food, the six storehouses, were all full. From all the country [round], the wealthy people came to buy food of me; and with various precious things, various swords, did they pay me well for the food. Every season doing [this], I had an overflow of precious things and swords in my house. I was [the most] uncommonly wealthy in all the land; in the country [where] I lived, [I was] a famous personage.</p>
</body>