<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB_XML/main/Schema/FFDB_mini.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB_XML/main/Schema/FFDB_mini.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<body>
<head>NEE023321</head>
<p>Bongso lived far away in the forest on her own. One day she walked to the river to bathe, she found some totn fruit on a stem and she ate them. If we eat seven totn fruit on one string we die. On her way home she met a totn woman. The totn woman gave a shirt and a sarong to Bongso. Then Bongso went home.</p>
<p>A few days later, Bongso's older sister came on a visit. She saw the shirt and the sarong and she wanted them. But Bongso would not give them to her; she knew that the woman who had given them to her was not truly a human being. Bongso was <ref target="g:GEE2143.032">putao</ref>, so she knew.</p>
<p>Her sister went in search of the woman who had given the clothes to Bongso, and when they met, the totn fruit woman gave her a bundle of clothes, inside which she had put many different kinds of little animals which bite. The clothes were full of bees, mosquitoes, wasps, leeches, and gnats and when the sister opened the bundle, they all flew out and bit her. They bit her everywhere and she died.</p>
<p>Bongso knew what had happened. She went to the totn fruit woman's house. "Come in, Bongso," said she when she saw her. "l will fetch some rice and cook you a meal," she added. While she was out of the house, Bongso gathered together all the clothes which contained the various stinging animals and set fire to them. The house caught fire and the totn woman burned. As she was burning, Bongso called out, "Become a true totn fruit!"</p>
<p>Then Bongso went to her sister's corpse, laid it out and blew magical smoke (<ref target="g:GEE2143.027">òz taba</ref>) all over it. She became alive again.</p>
</body>