<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB_XML/main/Schema/FFDB_mini.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB_XML/main/Schema/FFDB_mini.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<body>
<head>NEE023293</head>
<p>Once there lived jilœgen fruit woman deep inside the forest. She owned no clothes at all, and whenever people came close to her she would climb into her house in a jilœgen tree.</p>
<p>One day Bongso was out hunting. He came to a jilœgen tree. He heard a sound like "chung ren, chung ren"<note>This was said to be meaningless, and it was thought very funny by the teller and the audience.</note> and stopped to listen. When he looked up he saw the jilœgen woman up in the branches. She was defecating. When she saw him looking at her, she said, "Oh, it is you, Bongso." She put her hands in front to cover herself. She was very shy and did not want Bongso to see her naked. As she climbed down she picked a large leaf and placed this over her private parts. Bongso and the woman went together to her house in a jilœgen tree, and Bongso gave her his catch of the day, one leaf monkey. She cooked the meat and they ate. Afterwards Bongso went to the river to bathe. While he was away, the woman made several blowpipe darts, and when Bongso returned and saw the darts he thought that the woman had a husband. "Where is your husband?" he asked her. "Oh, he is out in the jungle," she replied. When Bongso heard that she had a husband he agreed to spend the night in the house<note>Bongso is always portrayed as "very shy" in his relationship with women. This is associated with the belief that if a young man wants to become a great <ref target="g:GEE2143.032">putao</ref>, he must obtain spirit-guides and esoteric knowledge before he marries, and he must refrain from flirtations.</note>, but he went to sleep in the doorway. It began to rain. "Come over here, Bongso, you are getting wet," said the jilœgen woman. Bongso moved a little in from the door. Then lots of mosquitoes bit him. "Come over here, Bongso," said the woman, and he moved a little further inside. Then scorpions appeared near him. "Come here, come on top of me," called out the woman. "No, no, I am afraid your husband will find out," said Bongso. "I have no husband. I made the darts myself so that you would not leave," she explained. When he heard that, Bongso went over to the woman and they slept together. Bongso moved into her house in the jilœgen tree and they became husband and wife.</p>
</body>