<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB_XML/main/Schema/FFDB_mini.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB_XML/main/Schema/FFDB_mini.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<body>
<head>NEE023342</head>
<p>Once upon a time a young girl died. Her family buried her. On top of the grave they planted a rambutan fruit. The fruit took roots and became a tree. The tree flourished and after several years it had become a large fruit tree with lots of fruit. One day Bongso was out walking. He came across the rambutan tree. He climbed up and ate much fruit. The house of the ghost of the young girl was in the grave. Bongso picked enough fruit to fill his backbasket. This he brought home to his mother and father and older brothers and sisters to eat. "Mmmm, delicious fruit," they all said, "we'll go tomorrow and fetch lots more." "There is a large wasps' nest in the tree," said Bongso. "Oh, I am frightened of climbing the tree in that case," said some of the brothers. "I am not frightened," said another brother, "tomorrow I will go and smoke out the wasps."</p>
<p>In the morning he went to the rambutan tree. He put his backbasket, blowpipe and quiver on the ground and carefully started climbing the tree. "Where is the wasps' nest?" he wondered, but as he could not see one anywhere, he ate fruit until he was full. Then he got out his knife and was about to cut off a few branches to take home with him. Suddenly he heard a voice from below saying, "Leave some for me." He looked down and saw the eyes of the ghost staring up at him from the grave. They were horrible. They popped out of the head on long stalks and the eyelashes were even longer. He became cold all over and the hairs on his head stood on end with fear. He climbed down from the tree as fast as he could and ran home. The ghost took his backbasket, blowpipe and quiver and put them inside her house. "I did not manage to climb the tree," lied the brother when he reached home empty-handed, "there were too many wasps." "I'm not afraid," said another brother, "I'll go tomorrow and smoke the wasps out."</p>
<p>The following morning he set off. When he reached the rambutan tree, he left his backbasket, blowpipe and quiver on the ground and climbed up. "Where is the wasps' nest?" he wondered, but as he could not see it anywhere he ate fruit until he was full. Then he took out his knife and as he was about to cut off some branches to take home with him, he heard a voice from below. "Leave some for me," it said. He looked down and saw the eyes of the ghost looking up at him from the grave. They were horrible. They popped out of the head on long stalks, and the eyelashes were even longer. He also became cold all over and the hairs on his head stood on end with fear. He climbed down as fast as he could and ran home. The ghost took his backbasket, blowpipe and quiver and put them inside her house with those of the brother from the day before. When the man reached home, he lied to the rest of the family saying that he had not managed to climb the tree because there were too many wasps. A third brother then declared that he was not frightened and that he would go the following day to smoke out the wasps. the same thing happened to him while he was up in the tree, and he also lied when he returned empty handed. Two other brothers suffered the same fate. Then Bongso decided to go back to the rambutan tree. He entered the house of <pb n="104"/>the ghost. Bongso was <ref target="g:GEE2143.032">putao</ref>, he knew that the ghost lived in the grave under the tree. He had seen her the first time he went there, but he did not want to tell his brothers. The ghost was not ugly when Bongso looked at her, only when the brothers did. She was very beautiful with long hair and clear skin. She gave Bongso a good meal of rice and they ate together. When they had finished eating, Bongso saw all the backbaskets, blowpipes and quivers. "Oh, those belong to my brothers," he said. He then climbed the tree and filled all the baskets with fruit and brought them home with the other things. "I found these on the ground," he told them. "Did you see the ghost?" asked the brothers. "Ghost? What ghost?" asked Bongso.</p>
<p>The next day all the brothers refused to go to the rambutan tree. They were all frightened of the ghost. So Bongso went again. He entered the ghost's house [the grave]. The girl-ghost gave him <plant latin="manihot utilissima">tapioca</plant> and meat. She had no difficulties in obtaining meat. It came by its own accord to her. After he had eaten, Bongso climbed the tree and took a lot of fruit. Then he and the ghost slept together. She became his wife. The next day they returned together to Bongso's house. When they arrived they had a meal together and then the wife entered the house. One of the brothers came over to Bongso's house to borrow some poison for his darts. He saw that two people had eaten. "Are you a couple, Bongso?" he asked. "No, there is just me," replied Bongso. "You have not got a wife?" "No," lied Bongso. The wife was inside the house so the brother could not see her. When he returned to his mother's house, he told her, "I think Bongso has a wife, I saw that two people had eaten together." "Where did he meet her?" the mother wanted to know. "I don't know," said the brother. The next day the mother went over to Bongso's house and she met her new daughter-in-law, but Bongso would not tell his mother where he had met his wife.</p>
<p>The following day Bongso went hunting. His sister wanted to see her new sister in-law so she went visiting. the two women talked together. "Oh, I am so hot here, sister-in-law," said the wife. She ran away. She went up to Moso Awan [Earth Six] for it is cool up there<note>girl. Had she been she would able to to Earth Six. She is a, hence her dislike of the heat Earth Seven. Ordinary ghosts do not continue to live in to the Afterworld.</note>. Bongso followed after her, but he could not find her anywhere. She had gone to the house of Ta' Hala. In the evening Bongso and his friends in Moso Awan conducted a <ref target="g:GEE2143.025">nöpoh</ref>. Bongso was singing. His <ref target="g:GEE2143.036">ruwai</ref> went here and there, but he could find his wife nowhere. The wife was in fact sitting right next to him all the time he was singing, but he did not think to look there and the others did not tell him. When the nöP0h was over the wife returned to Hala before Bongso could see her. During the day Bongso continued his search. He arrived at Ta' Hala's house, but the wife had run into the fields when she saw him coming. So he returned to the others. In the evening they did a <ref target="g:GEE2143.025">nöpoh</ref> again. Bongso sang. His <ref target="g:GEE2143.036">ruwai</ref> went here and there but he still could not find his wife. She was <pb n="105"/>sitting right next to him as she had the night before, but his <ref target="g:GEE2143.036">ruwai</ref> never looked there. When the <ref target="g:GEE2143.025">nöpoh</ref> was over, the returned to Ta' house before Bongso could see her.</p>
<p>The next day Bongso again went searching for his wife and he could not find her anywhere. When he came to Ta' Haws house the wife ran and hid so that he did not see her. In the evening they conducted a <ref target="g:GEE2143.025">nöpoh</ref> again. This time Bongso looked next to him and he saw his wife sitting there.</p>
<p>The following morning Bongso went to Earth Seven where he collected his mother and brought her to Earth Six. Here they all lived from then on. It was nice and cool there and they could eat fruit all the time.</p>
</body>