<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB_XML/main/Schema/FFDB_mini.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB_XML/main/Schema/FFDB_mini.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<body>
<head>NEE027831</head>
<p>I was a god [that] owned the upper sky. Many gods there were. Looking round [at those] that lived on the shores of the gods, [seeking] a goddess to match me, no goddess was there. In the lower regions, the regions of men, at last Samajekuru's younger sister, though truly a daughter of man, <pb n="156"/>by her face this woman at last [was] a match for me. A very goodly woman was she.</p>
<p>I descended to [those] lower regions. In the courtyard of Samajekuru's house, were many fishes, hanging from a pole to freeze. Samajekuru, with his younger sister, had gone hunting [and] was not [there]. I arrived at the empty house. I thought that Samajekuru, being a man, would be inferior [to myself] in magical power, [and so] I went to the pole [from which] the frozen fish [were hanging]. One of a pair of large salmon I cast on to the ground, and I turned myself into [the other] one of that pair of large salmon.</p>
<p>After, when I had remained [there some time], Samajekuru with his younger sister arrived, bearing great burdens of bear's flesh. Through the window in the back wall - through the window he handed his burdens of bear's flesh. Samajekuru's younger sister hastened through the door [to the window to receive it]. These people were tired, these people kindled the fire. Samajekuru said: "As I am [always] eating only flesh, I am disgusted. Bring a frozen fish, I will eat".</p>
<p>Samajekuru's younger sister came out. Having come to the pole with frozen fish, she looked carefully at the fishes, and took me down. Having taken me down, she carried me <pb n="157"/>in. Samajekuru said [that] frozen fish was chilly, [and that she] had to warm it: so said he. So she tied a string to my tail, attached it to a pothook, and attached me upside down.</p>
<p>Afterwards, Samajekuru said: "Fire there is little as yet; bring much wood, and kindle a great fire". Samajekuru's younger sister went out to bring in the wood. With an armful of wood did she enter, she kindled a great fire, and my head became hot! Puttsee-e! In that way did they burn me.</p>
<p>When my soul rose upwards to my tail, when I was near being burnt completely, affrighted. I split the back roof of the house with a [loud] noise, and got outside; towards the upper sky, spreading a [loud] noise, I ascended. Having gone into my house, I was angry. "Samajekuru! is a man born of that miserable earth, whereas I am a mighty god.</p>
<p>Being so - I thought that Samajekuru being a man born of miserable earth, would be inferior to me in magical power, and he has been my superior in [that] magical power". I had <pb n="158"/>angry thoughts; and so again I descended. Samajekuru, with his younger sister, had gone a-hunting, [and] was not [there], I arrived at the empty house. Then I hid a bowl of Samajekuru's, and transformed myself into one. And I remained and waited.</p>
<p>At last Samajekuru, with his younger sister, was heard coming. As they came along the house, through the window he let in his burden of bear's flesh. Samajekuru's younger sister [hastened] through the door to receive [it at the window]. [These] people were tired, [these] people made a great fire. Samajekuru said to bis younger sister. "Before [now], in the morning before we went hunting, didst thou wash my vessel?" - " I washed [it] not", Samajekuru's sister answered.</p>
<p>"If so, make some water hot, and wash my vessel". So said he. So, standing up and pouring much water into her great pot, she set the pot upon the fire, and made it boil. When [the water] boiled, she took down the vessel of her elder brother. I thought, "if they put me thus into that boiling pot, then I die": thought I.</p>
<p><pb n="159"/>Into the pot did [they] cast me; from the inside of the pot I rose up. I split the front roof of the house with a loud noise, went outside: towards the sky, the upper sky, spreading a [loud] noise, I ascended. My celestial house did I enter. Having entered, I thought within myself: "Samajekuru, being a man, [should be] inferior to me in magical power! so I thought. Yet Samajekuru, [is] a powerful being, stronger than I".</p>
<p>Having angry thoughts, I meditated within myself; and then decided that I would no longer jest, [but] would descend openly appearing in my body, my divine body. And therefore went I down. Having gone down, I stood in the courtyard of [that] house. Standing [there], I would not enter as a guest. Samajekuru's younger sister came out, [and] said:</p>
<p>"If thou wilt not enter as a guest, and hast come in anger, then I lead thee not into the house. My little iron house [stands] there; if thou wilt go in and sit there, - well". I went into that little house; it was dark [when] I went into the house; there I sat. In my soul I thought to myself that I was <pb n="160"/>wroth with Samajekuru: "I am a powerful god; and Samajekuru is a man born on this miserable earth; and [yet] in magical powers hath he defeated me". In myself did I think [thus], I sat, [and] resolved to say [that to him].</p>
<p>Just then: "What a smell of dung there is! Yet I thought I had entered a little silver house. What is that smell of dung?" Afterwards, when I looked round, I found I had entered a privy. From head to foot, Samajekuru together with his sister dirtied me from above.</p>
<p>Yet I was a mighty god, and Samajekuru a man born on this miserable earth, thought I; in magical power had he quite defeated me. Thus thinking, "Whatever I do, I cannot conquer Samajekuru in magical power. Therefore I was wroth. Therefore I was sitting in this place".</p>
<p>So I split with a [loud] noise the roof of the house, of that privy, and ascended to the sky, to the upper sky, spreading a noise as I went. I arrived at my home. Beginning from [my] head, all [my] body was foul with dung. Therefore I took off my iron vestments, washed my head <pb n="161"/>with water; I washed my body also; my iron vestments also did I wash.</p>
<p>Then going into my house, being angry, being wroth, I sat [there]. My divine elder brothers said: "When we passed the courtyard of our house, [we smelt] a smell of dung"; [so I] heard them say. Though I heard, [yet] did I not go out. With abashed soul, having that only in mind, I sat.</p>
<p>Afterwards, when I was sitting one day, my eldest brother coming chid me. "And wherefore? ... when Samajekuru being powerful and in magical power stronger than any god ... thou art foolish that thou hast thus behaved to Samajekuru!" Thus saying, he chid me.</p>
</body>