<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB_XML/main/Schema/FFDB_mini.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB_XML/main/Schema/FFDB_mini.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<body>
<head>NEE028171</head>
<p>There were three men. One was younger; the [other] two were elder [folks]. The younger, [who was] a sick man, had a house to himself; the two elder ones had a house to themselves. They listened to [news from] another village [in the district] of Turupa. Every night the dogs barked. In a distant village of Turupa, the dogs barked nightly. This news did [the men] get from the birds. When one day they <pb n="239"/>were sitting [together], a wealthy man from that other [village of] Turupa, arrived.</p>
<p>He told them [that] now, at the [one] end of his village, an infectious disease had broken out; at the [other] end of his village likewise had an infectious disease broken out. So [he asked] the rich men of Rurupa, having [the protection of] a god, to find some [remedy]. The people took thought. The two elder rich men - the younger man stuck a short sword in his girdle, the elder man stuck a longer sword in his girdle - went together to the village of the other rich man of Rurupa.</p>
<p>[The youngest man speaks]. Afterwards I alone remained, being that wretchedly ailing man, - I slept. And I saw a vision. A poor man from the forest of our village gave me in [my] dream an earthen sword. [Thus] did I dream. I woke: beside me lay an earthen sword. Having taken [it], I put it in my bosom. To the place whither my elders had gone, went I on their track; I went to the other village [of the district] of Turupa; I got to the edge of the village.</p>
<p>Meanwhile the younger of my elder brothers came running; following [and] pursuing my brother, [there came] <pb n="240"/>a beast with six tails. I made way for my elder brother. I seized the thing in my bosom: with [my] earthen sword, I struck the six-tailed beast; just in the middle did I cut it in two. My elder brother saluted me. We returned together to the other village [of the district] of Turupa; we returned; I went with my elder brother to a house.</p>
<p>I went to the [other] end of the village. Meantime, my eldest [brother] came running. When I looked towards him, [I saw that] a six-tailed beast was likewise pursuing my eldest [brother]. I retired to one side of the road. I seized the thing [that was] in my bosom. The lower jaw [of the beast] touched earth, the upper jaw touched the clouds; it came. I likewise seized the earthen sword, I struck the six-tailed beast just in the middle, I cut it through.</p>
<p>My elder brother saluted me, he thanked me. We returned; to the other village of Turupa we returned. Much did they wonder at me, the man [who was] so wretchedly ailing: the strong rich men could not kill the six-tailed beast; the poor sick man had been [so] valiant [as to do it]. Now I heard <pb n="241"/>how the rich man of the other village in Turupa said [he] would give his daughter to wife to the poor sick man.</p>
<p>Having heard, I thanked. The rich man of Far Turupa gives his daughter to wife to my second [brother], they said. The rich man at one end of our village gives his daughter to the eldest [brother], they said; [all] was right. - Two days we spent [there]; I went away together with my wife. My elder brothers and their wives - [we] all went away. The people living in all the villages wondered at me still more, I heard.</p>
<p>I became a great rich man, yet more than [my forefathers] did before. My elder brothers were poor. But I, [who] had before been so wretchedly ailing, am now the greatest rich man. I had two children. I taught my children [to do] as the ancestors did. My elder brothers also had two children each. They taught [them to do] as the ancestors did; we became old, [and] died. [My] children after me live yet more happily [than I].</p>
</body>