<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB_XML/main/Schema/FFDB_mini.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB_XML/main/Schema/FFDB_mini.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<body>
<head>NEE027812</head>
<p>[There] was a village. In a house [there] lived two men, brothers. Then [they] were very skilful in bear-hunting, they killed bears, piercing [them] with the lance only; [also], when they went seal-hunting in a boat on the sea, [or] on the ice, [they] killed many seals. Although [perhaps there] were brave people in [other] villages, [there] was no man [who] did as [valiantly as] did those [two] men. They [were] very lucky and brave men besides.</p>
<p>Now the people were one day sitting in the house, doing nothing. The next day they went fishing [for] large salmon. The woman of that house went out to gather tubers of the Corydalis ambigua. [There was] a village with one single mountain [in the neighbourhood]. So [she] gathered the tubers on the slope [of the mountain]. When she gathered the tubers, [there] came a man from the forest. A young man with a beard, a black beard, [who] asked the woman [for her] pipe: "Give thy pipe, I will give thee [wherewith to] smoke".</p>
<p>The woman was afraid of this man, [her] heart throbbed. <pb n="117"/>The woman took the pipe herself [and] puting tobacco into the pipe from a leather ponch, smoked the tobacco. Now the man smoked his tobacco. Now they have finished smoking Then again [he] asked for her pipe, [but] she would not in any wise. Although [she] would not, [he] took her pipe into his hands. This man put tobacco into her pipe. Thereupon he stretched [it out] to her. Afterwards that man struck a light [from a flint], striving to be foremost. Having struck the light first, he stretched out, [giving] her the fire. Although she would not [have it], he stretched out and took that fire and kindled her pipe [and] smoked the tobacco.</p>
<p>From the time of smoking the tobacco she quite lost consciousness. Hitherto she had been afraid of the man; and now, having smoked [his] tobacco, all that timid feeling was no [more]. Now that man kissed her. She had more fondness for him. Now [he] helped her to gather the tubers of the Corydalis ambigua. [And] very soon they gathered a great basket full of tubers of Corydalis ambigua.</p>
<p>Now that man [wished for] copulation, [and they] have copulated. Now the man said he wanted to marry her at once. <pb n="118"/>Now that woman came down to her house, and that man went up [back] to the forest. The woman, having come to [her] house, did eat. [And she said]: "When I had done, I went to the store-house; and having taken a basket for the tubers of the Fritillaria Kamtschatensis plant, I carried it into the house. A so-called made-dish; as many as were of these my tubers, of them all did I make the made-dish. There was much of this made-dish in the kneading-trough.</p>
<p>My husbands, after I had gone to gather the tubers, again went out to catch seals [and] now they entered, [and] had killed plenty of seals. Every day I took the wet shoes of my husbands, and hung [them] up. That day, although my husbands entered, I did not approach, I was busied in preparing the made-dish. Although [their] shoes were wet, I did not dry [them].</p>
<p>My younger sister - she alone - having cooked the meat, gave to eat [to] my husbands. All the people of the house ate all the meat, the people from other houses were invited to eat the meat. When all the people had finished eating the meat [and] I had meantime finished preparing the made-dish, at once I put that made-dish into wooden vessels, and gave <pb n="119"/>to all the people to eat. Now when [the meal] was over, the people from the other houses went away.</p>
<p>[One] hushand of mine now went to sleep; all the people went to sleep, and I went to sleep near the hearth, girt with a girdle. My husband having risen again, told me some pleasant words; he would sleep with me; so said [he]. Although my husband said so, I would not hearken at all. After that my husband, having gone, slept on the bed, and I slept near the hearth.</p>
<p>Now at day-break my husband, having risen, ate with [his] younger brother. They went a fishing for large salmon. And my younger sister said to my husband: "Do not go anywhere to day; remain but one day at home without working [outside]; yesterday thy wife having gathered tubers ... when she came thence, I saw her looks, all [her] looks were quite changed. Therefore to-day, for one day only, remain at home without working [outside]". Although my younger sister said this, they did not hearken, [they] went away at once [and] went to catch large salmon". [The younger sister says:] <pb n="120"/>"Thereupon I remained with my elder sister. [She] put the made-dish on to a vessel of birch-bark, [she] put in [till] it was full. [She] dressed herself in new clothes only. After, all she had of ear-rings, she put [them] all in [her] ears, so in [her] ears there were many. A girdle studded with rounds of metal did [she] put on. Having finished at last, she went out, carrying the bark-vessel with the made-dish. After that, my elder sister spoke thus to me: "If thou go out into the yard with me, that man ... yesterday gathering tubers I met a man - [that] being so, because he wished to marry me, [and] I having consented, now already he has married me. [That] being so, if I go out, look, where I shall go [into the forest]". Now I went out, when I had looked [around I saw] a young man, a black-bearded man, was to be seen behind the inau.</p>
<p>There [staying] he beckoned, calling my elder sister, [and] my sister now went towards that man. After she had gone there, that man - the made dish [she had] put into the bark-vessel - now that man ate. Having finished now, that man struck my <pb n="121"/>elder sister with [his] hand, [and] she became a she-bear. Then the man struck himself and became a he-bear. After [he] had struck [his] wife with [his] hand [and] gone the first [leading the way], she followed [him]. The two bears went one after another. After that I entered the house and waited for the men of the household.</p>
<p>Now near evening the male people entered with a load of large salmon. Now therefore I cooked the food; having finished, I gave them to eat. Now therefore I told them: "Before this morning, when I said thus to you 'Only one day remain at home' and you did not hearken to me ... well, yesterday thy wife whilst gathering tubers, met with a man, and they helped each other to gather the tubers; and after she came down and entered [and] prepared that made-dish; yesterday all the people [ate it] and you also ate. That being so, I wished to leave you at home but you, not having consented, you went to catch large salmon; afterwards you went out; then my elder sister, putting in the bark-vessel the made-dish [which] she had prepared yesterday, put [till it was] full, and [then] left [it] all night.</p>
<p><pb n="122"/>To-day, being alone at home, I was called by my elder sister: "Come outside with me", so said [she]; all the ear-rings also in all the ear-holes [did she] put in; after [she] dressed [in] all [her] new robes; then I went outside into the yard; one young man was standing behind the inau. When [he] beckoned, calling my elder sister, my elder sister went towards that man. That man now ate that made-dish; after [he] struck [his] wife, [she] became a she-bear. The man turned [and] struck himself [and] became a he-bear, and [away they] went. After that, having entered the house, behold, I have been awaiting you".</p>
<p>Now she has finished [her] relation to the [two] brothers. After that, the younger man chid exceedingly: "The so-called bear creature [that] with a pike I have [oft] pierced and borne home! The bear! so having taken my elder's brother's wife, it is now gone with her! And yet from [my] childhood did I pierce and bring home [those] so-called bear-creatures, like mice that live in the house ... What! a bear is now [so <pb n="123"/>suddenly] insolent to me? Come what may, I will go on its trail to the place where it lies".</p>
<p>Twelve valiant men only - ten of them bearing provisions on their backs, and all carrying pikes, and also carrying bows, as many as there were men, went upon the way on which the bear had gone. Two months, three months did they go, yet they came not to the place where that bear was. And their provisions were quite gone. Ten men went back home, two men only went on, following the bear's trail.</p>
<p>Having gone on for two days, three days, they went forward eating nothing. That being so, [the younger brother said] "[Hence!] go back! I alone will go on the trail so far as the bear has gone". "Then my companions went down seawards, going back. I alone continually went on the bear's trail. Six days I ate not. As I went upwards along the higher parts of the bed of a stream, there was [to be seen] a bear's den. I went to the threshold and looked in. That wife of my <pb n="124"/>brother - so soon! - had got two children. The husband lay on his back, sleeping beside his wife.</p>
<p>Thereupon, standing at the threshold, I looked: an old man and an old woman were sitting inside, and I stood and chid them: "Wherefore hast thou taken from me my brother's wife, and led her away with thee? That being so, now come out, and we shall fight, I with thee, till death; if we fight ... we shall see".</p>
<p>Now therefore there was heard inside that dwelling the grumbling of this old man. After [he] threw a box outside, [and said to] me: "If thou wilt go down to thy house, taking that box, and when thou wilt ask for another woman in any village, thou wilt also marry [her]; with thy elder brother - you will both marry. That is so: because my son loves the wife of thy brother, they are now married.</p>
<p>That being so, now I give thee this box. I am a bear. Although thou thinkest [that] I have nothing, yet a part of <pb n="125"/>my goods I give for a remembrance. Therefore do not be angry against me"".</p>
<p>Nevertheless the man who was standing outside wished only to fight.</p>
<p>[The old man, continuing]. "Because thou dost so, I will give thee again one box more. Now, when there are two boxes [given] if thou [wouldst] a little further withdraw thy anger into thy soul, [it were] well".</p>
<p>[The younger brother speaks]. "Nevertheless, standing at the threshold of the den, I wished but to fight. After, the old man grumbled: „Then thou art a man, and wishest only to fight; but if [it] be a real fight, thou wilt die. Although for me ... if thou kill me [and] although [I] shall die, afterwards I shall be alive; again I shall be alive. Thou dying but once, wilt die entirely. Therefore do not wish exceedingly to make a fight".</p>
<p>Nevertheless, standing [there] and speaking only [about] of fighting, [I was told] at last by that old man: "If people love to fight; well then, a fight [let there be]". Then that old <pb n="126"/>man awakened his son. "Rise up quickly! At present the man [who] followed thee is on the threshold of our house, and he is [here], wishing to fight with thee". Although he said so, the man did not rise.</p>
<p>The man's wife said: "Then I going outside shall fight with the man [who] wishes to fight". But the old man would not: "Being a woman having just borne a child, if you go outside to that man, and when [they] are together [by] the blood that has magic, and [by] the spray that has magic force, that man will see!" Thus spoke the old man, [and] the woman rising at once came outside. When I stood at the threshold of the [bear's] den, the woman came out to me.</p>
<p>[There it] came out [with her] a spray of magic power, I could not even look [at her]. This only I remembered; what took place [after]. I know not. At last I awoke. Lying in the great bed of a stream, at the bottom of the riverbed, I slept lying on [my] back. When I fell asleep again, I saw the following dream:</p>
<p>That old man [said]: "Thou earnest [here] following thy <pb n="127"/>brother's wife, and wishing only to fight, so thou hast got that from the woman. [That] being so, [I might] leave thee without any compensation, but I have pity on thee. Therefore, when, having risen, thou goest down to the sea, I shall give thee a bear-cub. When thou beginnest to go up the mountain slope, then thou wilt catch a bear-cub, two bear-cubs, three bear-cubs; going further to [thy] village, again thou wilt catch a bear-cub, two bear-cubs, three bear-cubs, [in] all thou wilt catch five bears; then [in all] ten bears.</p>
<p>When thou wilt come to thy village, if the people living in the neighbourhood, [if] all the men bring up these bear-cubs, [it will be] good. I will give thee also slain bears until thy death. In a year ... I shall give thee sixty bears a year. Sea creatures also shall I give thee. After that, every year, when thou preparest many skins, when thou wilt sell [them] to the Japanese lords, and when thou wilt possess the wealth of the Ainus; [then] if thou wilt go to seek a wife in any village, and wilt buy a goodly woman now with the wealth [acquired] by thy hands - [then] also thou wilt cause thyself to be fed [by her]. <pb n="128"/>If thou goest back to the village with her, and if thou hast children [by her], and [they] likewise after thee shall go hunting [or fishing]; unto them shall I give little bear-cubs, as I do unto thee"".</p>
<p>Now therefore he has married, and has had children. He has had daughters, and [others] have taught them, but his sons has he taught [himself]; the daughters were taught by the woman. So they spent their life, grew old, and afterwards died.</p>
<p>Afterwards, the sons went hunting in the forest, like their father; every year [they] brought in sixty bears. In the sea also did they hunt [with] like [good luck]. Now his children having died, the people who lived after them when [their ancestor] heard of them [in the other world] did as [he] had done [according to what] he heard. Now it is heard that these people lived very wealthily. Now he lived [in the other world] not disquieted as to what [happened] after them. Now therefore, if people live thus well, it is very good.</p>
</body>