<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB_XML/main/Schema/FFDB_mini.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB_XML/main/Schema/FFDB_mini.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<body>
<head>NIP028784</head>
<p>Bütha the lissome and soft-eyed was promised to Murree, the swift-in-pursuit-of-game, and the time was at hand when he could claim her, for he was now coming back from a Boorah. Back from the tests of courage, back as a brave of his tribe, back with a right to marry. Back to disappointment; back to despair. For first to meet him was Gubbee, the father of Bütha. First to tell him the news of Bütha, his promised one. Told how she had been hunting for honey. How she had come to the nest of a Bubburr, whence she had taken some eggs, bringing them even into the camp. How, just as those who knew of the danger rebuked her for touching these, gliding into their midst had come the mammoth snake Bubburr.</p>
<p>Past them all, straight to Bütha went Bubburr, coiled his form round hers, crushing the life from her. Then swiftly went he as he had come, leaving Bütha, the lissome and soft-eyed, lifeless before them.</p>
<p>"Am I in time for the burial?" said Murree.</p>
<p>"Three times has <ref target="g:GIP0247.137">Yhi</ref> slept since we buried her," said Gubbee.</p>
<p><pb n="77"/>"Then she is even now travelling towards Weebulloo, the heaven of women. I shall be swift to follow her. The <plant><ref target="g:GIP4128.041">dheal</ref></plant> twigs are yet green on her path. I shall snatch her yet from Weebulloo."</p>
<p>"Think you," said Gubbee scornfully, "that she who was murdered will follow one who has not avenged her?"</p>
<p>Then Murree paused from slaying himself as he stood, and he said: "There is wisdom in your words, O Gubbee, father of She-who-is-lost. I shall first slay Bubburr, the snake demon." Thus saying, Murree turned to the camp of his tribe.</p>
<p>The days passed, and Bütha was still unavenged. But Murree never forgot her. Nor did he cast one glance on the comeliest of maidens. His heart was with Bütha in Weebulloo. His mind was bent on revenge.</p>
<p>He went hunting with two of his tribe. At length he saw what he wished for ahead of him. A nest of the Bubburrs was there. He did not run straight to attack it, as his mullayerhs expected, but went back with them to the camp.</p>
<p>"Come," he said to his tribe, "come and let us gather the gum of Mubboo."</p>
<p>He told them then why he spoke so, and, seeing his reason was good, they followed him. Having gathered the gum in plenty, they carried it back to their camp.</p>
<p>Next day they went with Murree, and at his bidding broke down the branches of trees some distance from the nest of the Bubburrs. With these branches they made platforms on the boughs of some trees which he showed them. They went on to these platforms, and the noise they made was great; hearing which out came the snakes, <pb n="78"/>the mammoth Bubburrs. Murree and the <ref target="g:GIP4128.035">Daens</ref> had been careful that no shadow of theirs should fall on the ground. They knew well that the bite of even their shadows by a Bubburr would kill them.</p>
<p>As the Bubburrs came nearer, and nearer, the <ref target="g:GIP4128.035">Daens</ref> made ready pieces of gum, gum of the Mubboo, about the size of a pigeon's egg, to throw at their mouths. Snap went the jaws of the Bubburrs at them. Another pellet of gum was thrown. Snap! and the jaws, the jaws of death, were closed, held fast by the gum between them. The murderous Bubburrs were mastered. Murree the avenger had conquered.</p>
<p>Seeing the scheme had worked as they wished, the <ref target="g:GIP4128.035">Daens</ref> returned to their camp. There they waited patiently, returning in due time to the scene of their gum throwing. They were laden with wood, for they expected to find their enemies dead, and the flesh of Bubburrs was good. Great was the joy of Murree when he saw the gum had stuck their jaws fast, and that the Bubburrs were all dead. His hand was swift to raise his <ref target="g:GIP4128.032">comeboo</ref>, and sever their heads from their bodies. Swift, too, were the <ref target="g:GIP4128.035">Daens</ref> in lighting fires for cooking the Bubburrs.</p>
<p>Scarce have Bubburrs been in the land since Bütha the lissome and soft-eyed was avenged by the cunning of Murree the swift-to-hunt-game.</p>
<p>Though their name carries terror yet to its hearer. Their size has grown with the time, and fear has stretched their measurements, until even the strongest and wariest feel a tremour when the name of the brown and yellow Bubburr is mentioned.</p>
</body>