<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB_XML/main/Schema/FFDB_mini.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB_XML/main/Schema/FFDB_mini.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<body>
<head>NNA026112</head>
<p>A man was out hunting. He had a wife and four children. He could find no large game. All he could get were small birds, sometimes only one or two a day. They were starving, and moved their camp. The woman found a bear's den. She heaped a pile of snow over it to conceal it, and camped alongside. Her husband was hunting. That night he heard near the head of the bed growling as of dog. He asked his wife what it might be, and she answered that she was scratching herself. They were to move camp again the next day. In the morning her husband went ahead to try to find some game. He was barely out of sight when the woman killed the bear. She cooked the meat. Her husband smelled the burning hair and meat, and came back. As soon as she saw him, she hid the bear, and put the head of one of her children into the fire and scorched his hair. She told her husband that one of the boys had gone too close to the fire and had singed his hair. When he saw the boy with his hair burnt, he believed what she said, and departed. The woman fed herself and children, and put the rest of the meat on her toboggan. Now, her brothers were also starving, and, thinking that their brother-in-law might be well provided with game, they journeyed towards his camp. When they struck his trail, they followed it, and came to the place where their sister and her children had been eating the bear-meat. They saw the bear's skull hanging there. They were glad, and thought that their brother-in-law had been successful in hunting. The woman concealed the bear-meat from her husband, and kept it for herself and her children. When her brothers arrived in camp, they said to their brother-in-law, "We are starving;" and she answered, "So am I." They said, "We saw the skull of a bear that you had killed, and we thought you had meat." Then the woman said, "I will give you some meat to eat," and she took some out of her toboggan. The brothers were ashamed, and went off without eating. Then the husband killed her and the children, because she had hidden the food and deceived him.</p>
</body>