<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB_XML/main/Schema/FFDB_mini.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB_XML/main/Schema/FFDB_mini.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<body>
<head>NNA024571</head>
<p>The Puma had a wife and son. He went out hunting with son. The Bear came to his tent. He saw the Puma's wife and fell in love with her. "I wish to have her," he thought. Then he went to where she was sitting. He proposed to run away with her. She consented, and they went off together. Then the Puma came back. He could not find his wife. He thought, "Perhaps she has eloped with the Bear." He saw no tracks. He looked all about; then he found their tracks. Very angry, he followed them. Then a high wind came and he lost their tracks. Next day he found the tracks again and went on. "Perhaps they are in that cedar wood," he thought. Approaching it, he heard voices. He knew them as his wife's and the Bear's. Then he sent his son to make a circuit, so as to come upon them from the other side, in order that the Bear might run towards himself. The woman was saying, "The Puma is very strong." "No; I am very strong," said the Bear. "No; he is strong," said the woman. So the Bear seized a cedar and tugged at it, lifted it, and threw it on the ground; but she said, "He is stronger than you." The Bear had his moccasins off. Then the young Puma came. Quickly the Bear put on his moccasins, but he put them on the wrong feet. On his fore feet also he interchanged the moccasins in his haste. Then he ran. The Puma was waiting for him. He rose up and grappled the Bear; he threw him to the ground. The Bear got up and came on again. The Puma seized him again. Now he threw the Bear to the ground and broke his back. Then he went to his wife and threw her down. Again he threw her down, and broke her back. Then he went away with his son.</p>
</body>