<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB_XML/main/Schema/FFDB_mini.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB_XML/main/Schema/FFDB_mini.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<body>
<head>NNA026058</head>
<p><note>See RBAE 31 : 702 (Bellacoola, Chinook, Haida, Nass, Tlingit, Tsimshian; also Shuswap, Takelma, Thompson).</note></p>
<p>Once, when Raven was travelling, he came to a house, and, looking in, saw no inmates. He noticed a fish-spear with a single-pointed harpoon-head of bone. He camped near by, and noticed the fish-spear lying in the same place near the entrance of the house every morning. It seemed as if it had been used during the night. Several times he went and looked at the spear. He tried to make one like it; but, each time he attempted to do so, he forgot how it was made. At last he thought, " I shall go there at dusk and steal it, and then I can copy it." He went into the house, which was not lighted in any way, but he could see a little. He saw no signs of fire, and no people. He seized the spear-head, and immediately a stick struck him on the leg. He thought it must have fallen on him accidentally from above. He went away with the spear-head, and received a hard tap on the leg. He persisted, and moved farther away. This time he received such a blow on the leg, that he fell down with his leg broken. Then a voice asked, "Why do you steal our spear-head?" Raven answered, "I wanted to copy it. I notice that you are fishing; and I cannot fish, for I have no spear-head." He added, "Where are you?" He felt about, but did not feel anything. The ghosts were talking to him, and he was in a house of ghosts.</p>
<p>The voice said, "I will help you." The ghost then took half the lower rib from one side of his body, and gave it to Raven, telling him, <pb n="226"/>"As soon as you sharpen it, it will change into a spear-head; but you must use it only at night. In the daytime it cannot spear fish." Raven went off lame, carrying the bone. This spear-head obtained from the ghosts was shown by Raven to the people, who copied it; and from this model were spear-heads made like those used by Indians now. This is why ravens have crooked legs and walk lame now. Had Big-Raven not been made lame by the ghost, ravens would not be lame now. This is also the reason why people and game have a small rib on their sides, underneath the others. This is the rib broken off by the ghost, and given to Raven to make the spear-head. This is also the reason why ghosts sometimes strike people and things at night, and also why ghosts are invisible. Had Raven seen them, they would be visible to us now.</p>
</body>