<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB_XML/main/Schema/FFDB_mini.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB_XML/main/Schema/FFDB_mini.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<body>
<head>NNA026050</head>
<p>It was fine weather; and Raven was travelling, sometimes in his canoe, sometimes walking. The weather made him drowsy, and he lay down to have a nap. He dreamed that a woman was sleeping with him. When he awoke, he saw nobody. Then he noticed his own reflection in the water, and thought it was the woman.<note>See BBAE 59 : 306 (Assiniboin, Bellacoola, Blackfoot, Caddo, Chilcotin, Comox, Haida, Kaska, Kwakiutl, Nootka, Ojibwa, Osage, Quinault, Shuswap, Thompson, Tsimshian; also references from other continents).</note> He said to it, "Come on, come here!" but it did not move. He moved towards it, and then it seemed to approach. He went into the water and met it. He seized it, and felt in the water right to the bottom, but could feel no woman. When he left the water, he saw it again. He did the same a second time. At last he thought the mud at the bottom must be she. He went in a third time, felt about at the bottom, and brought up mud. He tried to form a woman out of this mud; but, happening to look at the water, he saw the reflection, just as before. He thought this mud could not be she, for he had brought it up, and still the woman appeared to be there in the water. He became angry, and threw the mud at the reflection, saying, "Henceforth you shall be mud." Then he got in his canoe and paddled away in a dissatisfied and angry mood.</p>
<p>This is why mud is soft, and people sink in it. Had Raven finished the working of the mud into something, or made it hard, it would be different now. This is also the reason that some women are good-looking; and why, because of their looks, men are attracted to them, the same women are soft and useless. The Indians say, "They are like mud."</p>
</body>