<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB_XML/main/Schema/FFDB_mini.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB_XML/main/Schema/FFDB_mini.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<body>
<head>NNA026119</head>
<p><note>This story is said to belong to the Raven phratry and to be of Tlingit origin; at least, the Tlingit tell a similar story, and the families that tell it use goat-horns and goat-masks as crests. Probably they claim the deserted boy as one of their ancestors. The Tahltan refer to this story as an example of the good results that will accrue from strict observance of taboos (BBAE 39 : 262). See comparative notes in RBAE 31 : 785. Compare also following story, Kaska (JAFL 30 : 455), Thompson (JE 8 : 237).</note></p>
<p>An orphan boy lived with his grandmother.<note>Some people say that she was his only relative, but in the story an uncle is mentioned.</note> It was good weather; but the people were short of food, and therefore moved their camp. As the old woman was unable to walk, they deserted her, leaving her a little food, but no fire. They wanted to take the boy with them, but he would not leave his grandmother. The boy went outside of the village a little distance. Here he heard a sound, and, becoming afraid, he returned. That night he dreamed that some one talked to him, saying, "Why did you run away from the sound you heard? I want to help you. Leave your grandmother when she is asleep, and go to where you heard the sound." He awoke, and went to the place designated. When he reached there, he saw a house, which he entered. Within were many people. A well-dressed wealthy chief spoke to him, and asked why he staid with his grandmother. He answered, "Because she is my relative. I cannot desert her." The chief asked if they had any food; and he answered, "No." The chief said, "Well, you will starve, then." The boy answered, "I am willing to starve with my grandmother." The chief then told him, that, if he would do as he directed him, he would obtain plenty of food. He said, "Near your camp there is a deep canyon. Make your house <pb n="231"/>there between two steep rocks. Make it with sharp goat-horns,<note>The inference is not clear. It is thought they used sharp goat-horns for cutting the rocks or in some manner in the construction of the house, and perhaps in digging it.</note> but first abstain from food and drink for eight days. Then you will receive great power from me." He saw and heard all this as in a vision. When he awoke, he found himself lying on the ground, and neither house nor people were in sight. He thought he had been away a short time, but he had been absent several days. When he reached home, his grandmother asked him where he had been. She said, "I have been weeping for you many days. I thought you were dead." Now he fasted as directed; and when the eight days had passed, he caused wind and rain-storms to visit that part of the coast to which his uncle and the people had gone. They could neither fish nor hunt, and soon were short of food. Now he said to his grandmother, "We will move up the mountains, and make a house in a canyon there." She answered, "The mountains are far away, and I cannot walk." The country in the vicinity of where they were was flat. The boy said, "I will make the mountains come nearer." He stretched out his fingers and then contracted them; and the earth was contracted, so that the mountains stood close by. He said to his grandmother, " Now look out! " She looked, and saw that the mountains were now quite near by. Then he struck his grandmother's legs and body with brush, and she became able to walk like a young woman. They went to the canyon in the mountains near by. He told his grandmother what to do, and she built a house. Perhaps it was of stone, but it had a door which opened and shut. He said to her, " I am going to call the game into the house, but you must not kill the first animal that enters. Wait until all are in." He began to sing a song by means of which he called the game. Soon he said to his grandmother, "The game is coming. Open the door!" Then goats came in, and nearly filled the house. When all were in, he told her to shut the door and to kill them. She clubbed and butchered the game. The boy made his grandmother strong, so that she could skin and cut up the game quickly. He also made her able to carry all the meat and skins down and fill one of the houses of the deserted village. He asked his grandmother what kind of food she wished next; and she said, "Sheep." He sang; and sheep came, and filled the house in the same way. When all the sheep-meat had been stored, he asked his grandmother what she desired next; and she said, "Halibut." He said to her, "Go to the beach, and you will find them." She went, and found many halibut on the beach. Then he caused many olachen to come ashore. His grandmother dried the halibut. She put the olachen into a pit, where she let them rot until they were ready to be boiled for trying out the oil. The boy put the fish and oil in his uncle's house in the <pb n="232"/>village. Now the people were starving. The boy's uncle, who was chief, sent a male and a female slave back to the village to see if the old woman and boy were still alive, and to find out if there was any game. Meanwhile the boy and his grandmother had moved back to the village. The house which they had made in the canyon had vanished. The slaves arrived, and, seeing smoke, knew that the old woman and the boy must be alive. They looked into a house, and saw that it was full of meat. They found their master's house full of olachen and olachen-oil. They ate their fill, and took some along when they returned. The boy said to them, "Don't tell my uncle. Say I am dead." The slaves returned, and told the people that the old woman and boy were dead. They were asked if they had found their bodies; and they said, "Yes, they were lying in the house." After a while one of the slave-children cried for olachen. The chief heard him, and asked, "How does he know about olachen? " Then he said to the parents, "You are hiding something. If you do not tell me, I shall kill you." Then they told him all, and said that the boy had charged them not to tell. The people at once broke camp, and went aboard their canoes to return to the village. The younger wife of the boy's uncle dressed herself nicely and painted her face. When wiping her face with a towel, she scratched it with a shell that happened to be in the towel. When the people arrived at the village, the uncle said to his nephew, "Which one of my wives do you wish for your wife? " and he answered, "I don't want the younger one, because she always ill-treated me. I will take the elder one, for she was always good to me."<note>Compare the last part of this story with the Kaska tale "Story of the Water-Man*" (JAFL 30 : 460).</note> The boy's uncle gave him his elder wife, and appointed him to the inheritance of his family, name, and rank.</p>
</body>