<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB_XML/main/Schema/FFDB_mini.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB_XML/main/Schema/FFDB_mini.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<body>
<head>NNA019539</head>
<p><note>See Franz Boas, Indianische Sagen von der Nord-Pacifischen Küste Amerikas, p. 147; see also p. 83 of this volume.</note></p>
<p>In the beginning Xwāʼxwas was a salmon. When the Deluge came, it carried the salmon up the mountains. When the waters subsided, the salmon landed at Flat Place [Ōdzâʼᵋlîs] and began to build a house which he intended to name Only-House-on-Ground [ᵋnᴇʼmsgᴇmdzâʼlas]. He searched for stones to make a stone axe, and found some on the bank of the river. Then he began to hew two heavy posts for his house. He had his hair tied up in a knot on the back of his bead. While he was working, he suddenly heard a loud noise behind him, a short distance down the river. He turned round and saw a large thunder-bird which had alighted, each of his feet resting on one of two large bowlders that lay quite a distance apart. Then Xwāʼxwas said, "O master! I wish you were a man, so that you might help me in my work." Then the thunder-bird took off his feather garment and his mask, and showed his face. He said, "I will help you." He flew up and lifted in his talons a large log which Xwāʼxwas had cut for the beam of his house, and laid it on top of the post. Then he alighted again and took off his feather garment. He told his bird mask to fly back to the sky, and said, "You shall be heard when one of my descendants is about to die." Then the bird flew up into the sky. The man took the name Kunōʼᵋsila. He built a house at Flat Place, and both he and Xwāʼxwas became the ancestors of the G·īʼg·ilgam. Kunōʼᵋsila's son was Ēʼwagit, whose son was Wāʼxowit, whose son <pb n="473"/>was Aʼnxᵋanwîsagamēᵋ, whose son was Haʼmdzid, whose son was Yāʼgoʟas, whose daughter was ᵋnᴇʼmnasâlaga. She was the aunt of Nᴇg·äʼ, who told the story. One of the recent descendants of Xwāʼxwas was Yāʼqałᵋᴇnāla.</p>
</body>