<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB_XML/main/Schema/FFDB_mini.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB_XML/main/Schema/FFDB_mini.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<body>
<head>NNA024574</head>
<p>A man lived on a rock with his two grandsons. He told the boys, "You had better go hunting and bring something to eat. I am hungry. Go to the hills, sit on the top, and watch in all directions; then you may find something." Then the boys went off and watched in the brush. An elk came straight towards them. One of them said, "I see an elk. Let us kill it." The other said, "My older brother, let us run away. I am afraid." The older said, "No. Sit still. It is an elk. I shall shoot it, as our grandfather directed." The other one said, "No. I am afraid."</p>
<p>When the older was nearly ready to shoot, his younger brother fled, crying, "Let us run away. I am frightened." Then the elk started back. The older one said, "What is it? Are you crazy? I was nearly ready to shoot that elk." The younger said, "I was frightened; but I know now that it is an elk. Let us go after it; it cannot have gone far."</p>
<p>When they got near the elk again, the younger brother wanted to shoot at it. The older brother wanted him to stay behind, but did not persuade him. When they were ready to shoot, the younger again ran off shouting, and the elk escaped. The older brother <pb n=279>upbraided him; he nearly struck him. The younger said, "I was afraid that it would jump on me. I became frightened." Again he persuaded the older to take him with him. When they approached the elk another time, he again persuaded his older brother to allow him to shoot, saying, that if one of them missed, the other could still try to hit it. But the same thing happened as before. Then the older brother again became angry and reviled the younger. It was now sunset, but once again the younger persuaded the older to go after the elk; so they went around ahead of it. Then the older tied the arms and the legs of the younger, and tied up his mouth. The elk came close. The younger one began to emit smothered screams. Then the older brother hurriedly shot. He killed the elk. The younger was tossing about, trying to scream and to flee. "Are you crazy? I have killed the elk," said the older. "Have you really killed it?" asked the younger. Then he loosened his younger brother and showed him the elk. The younger said, "What kind of a deer is that?" The older said, "It is an elk. Hurry! Get some brush for a fire. Let us skin it and go home quickly. There may be bad persons about here." The younger said, "I will get some presently." Then the older said, "What is the matter with you? Get some brush so that we can go home." "I will get some presently," said the younger. Again the older said to him, "Make a fire quickly. I will roast some meat and eat it, then I will go home. Be quick!" "No. Presently. I want to rest now," said the younger. He would not help his older brother. So that one alone skinned the game and cooked some of the meat. Then he said, "Let us go home now. There may be bad things about. I am frightened." The younger said, "No. I am afraid to go. I cannot go home. Let us stay here for the night; there is nothing bad about here." Then the older urged him no more. He said, "Let us sleep in a cedar. Make a bed." The younger one agreed and made a bed in the top of the cedar, after they had buried the meat. Then they slept. In the middle of the night the younger one said, "I am hungry. I will go down to eat." The older said to him, "What is the matter with you? Eat to-morrow, sleep now." But the younger one insisted on going down to eat. Finally his older brother said, "Very well." Then the younger brother went down, made a large fire, and cooked a whole shoulder of the elk. He began to eat. Then there were cries from far off from all directions. The boy said, "What is it? Is anyone approaching? Come here! we will eat." The older brother remained in the cedar.</p>
<p>Then some one came to the opposite side of the fire. He was a large, long man. The younger brother said, "Come, my friend, eat; I have good food; sit down there." There was no answer. <pb n=280>"Here is something to eat," said the boy, holding it out to him. The person did not take it. He did not answer even when he was repeatedly spoken to. Then the boy hit him on the head and knocked him down. Coming closer, he then stood by his head, whereupon the man reached out and caught him with a violent grip, in scroto. "Oh! Oh I Let me go!" cried the boy. The man continued to hold him. "Do not hold me. Oh! Oh! You hurt me. Let me go. My older brother, come to help me. This is holding me." But his older brother was angry and did down. The man squeezed him harder, while the boy groaned. he walked off with him. The older brother heard his cries faint; then he ceased to hear them on account of the distance.</p>
<p>In the morning he came down from the tree. Crying, lowed the tracks. He saw that they led to a lake and right into it. He could go no farther. Going back and taking meat, he went home and told his grandfather. <note>The story makes him repeat what has been told. </note> His grandfather him, "We will go to-morrow to see that place." Then they to the lake and watched it. Then the old man said, "Wait while I go down, following the tracks." He was away until Then he came up, bringing a dead man, and laid him down. said, "This is the man that killed your brother. Deep killed him." Again he went into the lake and stayed until sunset. Then he came up with another. "This is the man that killed your brother," he said. "I entered his house and killed him. Now open his mouth and look at his teeth." The boy saw a little meat between the teeth. His grandfather said to him, "Take a stick and pick out the meat from his teeth." The boy did so and made a little pile of it. Then the old man told him to cut open the dead man. When he had done so, he asked him, "Do you see any bones or other parts? Pick them out." The boy did as he was told, and then did the same to the other man. They put the meat and bones into a hollow stone and carried it home. They left it standing outside, a short distance from the tent. Then they slept. Early in the morning his grandfather said, "He is shouting, Wuwuwuwu! Do you hear him?" "Yes," said the older brother. They answered with a shout. Then he came. "Well, my older brother," he said. He had arisen from the meat.</p>
</body>