<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB_XML/main/Schema/FFDB_mini.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB_XML/main/Schema/FFDB_mini.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<body>
<head>NNA025128</head>
<p>After <animal>Hawk</animal> had been killed, and the flood had subsided, people found that all fires were put out all over the world. Nothing could be cooked, but for a time people did not trouble about it. Then after a few days they began to talk about it, and sent <animal>Owl</animal> to <placeName>Mount Shasta</placeName> to look all over the world and see if he could find any trace of fire. <animal>Owl</animal> took a feather blanket and went. <animal>Lizard</animal> watched him go, and told the people how he was getting on. After a while, when <animal>Owl</animal> did not come back, people thought he was dead. But <animal>Lizard</animal> said, "Sh! I can still see him." <animal>Owl</animal> got to the top at last, very tired, and wet with sweat. <animal>Lizard</animal> saw him look all about. He looked west twice, and there saw smoke coming from a sweat-house. After a while <animal>Owl</animal> came down from the mountain, and, coming back, told people what he had seen.</p>
<p>Next morning all got ready and went off to the west, to where the smoke had been seen. Every one had a cedar-bark torch. <animal>Dog</animal> had some punk hidden in his car. Late in the evening they arrived at the house, and asked to be allowed to warm their hands. <animal>Dog</animal> held his ear down, and fire caught in the punk. Then every one thrust their torches into the fire, and ran. The people in the house were angry, and struck at them as they ran off. <animal>Coyote</animal>'s fire gave out first, then another's and another's, until finally all were out except that which <animal>Dog</animal> had in his ears. The people who owned fire had made it rain, and this put out the people's torches. No one knew that <animal>Dog</animal> had fire. They got home and were much troubled, for they thought the fire had all been lost. <animal>Dog</animal> was laughing, and said, "I am sweating." <animal>Coyote</animal> got angry at this, and said, "Hit him! Knock him out!" Then <animal>Dog</animal> said to <animal>Fox</animal>, "Look in my ear." When he did so, he saw the fire. He took out the punk, made fire from it, and so people got fire again.</p>
</body>