<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB_XML/main/Schema/FFDB_mini.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB_XML/main/Schema/FFDB_mini.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<body>
<head>NNA026029</head>
<p><note>See RBAE 31 : 674 (Comox, Haida, Kwakiutl, Newettee, Tlingit, Tsimshian). MAFLS 2 : 139 (Okanagon, Sahaptin, Sanpoil); also Tahltan (Emmons U Pa 4 : 119);</note></p>
<p>Raven travelled along the seashore. He knew of the salmon in the sea; and when he called them, they jumped out of the water. He thought he would try to catch one; so he went ashore on the beach, and called, "Come, friend, and jump on my belly!" The salmon jumped, and hit him so hard on the stomach that he was rendered unconscious for a time. When he came to his senses, the salmon was just about to enter the water again. He did the same thing again, with like result. Then he built a corral of stones on the beach, and lay down in the middle of it. Now he called for the third time, and the salmon struck him and again rendered him unconscious. When he revived, he saw the salmon jumping about in the corral, trying to get out. He clubbed and killed it.</p>
<p><pb n="206"/>Now Raven did not know how to cut up salmon. He defecated, and asked his excrements for advice.<note>See BBAE 59 : 294, note 5 (Chilcotin, Chinook, Flathead, Kaska, Kathlamet, Lillooet, Nez Percé, Okanagon, Shoshoni, Shuswap, Takelma, Thompson).</note> As soon as they began to speak, he held up his hand, and said, "Hush! I know." However, as soon as he began to cut the fish, he forgot what he had been told, and asked again. This happened many times in succession. At last, however, he listened to the end; and they said, "Make a cut around the neck to the bone, then around the tail the same way, then down the belly from one cut to the other. Take out the entrails and back- bone, and then hang up until the skin is dry. Dry well. Then split well, spread out flat, and hang up to dry in the wind and sun."</p>
</body>