<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB_XML/main/Schema/FFDB_mini.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB_XML/main/Schema/FFDB_mini.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<body>
<head>NNA026045</head>
<p><note>See also Emmons, Tahltan Indians, p. 119 : "Then Raven told the little birds that he was going to make man, but they did not believe him; and as he asked each one, 'Have you young inside?' they all answered 'No.' Then he turned to the rocks and the trees, and asked them the same question, and they both answered affirmatively; whereupon he told them the young first born would be man, and they each told him that at the break of day a child would be born. And so in the morning the tree first gave birth, and the offspring became man: therefore as the tree springs from the seed, lives, and dies, so human life is but for a season. Following the birth of the tree, the rock brought forth its offspring, which was of stone, and which was rejected by Raven as having everlasting life." See RBAE 31 : 663 (Haida, Nass, Tlingit, Tsimshian; also Rivers Inlet).</note></p>
<p>Once the Tree and the Rock were pregnant and were about to give birth. The Tree woman held on to a stick or bar, as Indian women do, while the Rock woman used nothing to hold on to. Her child, when half born, turned into a rock and died. Raven came along shortly afterwards, and found the women. He said, "I am very sorry. I have come too late. Had I been here, this would not have happened. Now people must die, because Tree gave birth, and Rock did not." If Rock had given birth, and Tree had not, people would never die. People would then have been like rocks, and lasted forever. As it is now, people are like trees. Some will live to be very old, and decay and die, as some trees do; while others, when only partly grown, will die like young trees that die without decay and fall down. Thus death comes to people at all ages, just as among trees, and none lives very long.</p>
</body>