<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB_XML/main/Schema/FFDB_mini.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB_XML/main/Schema/FFDB_mini.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<body>
<head>NNA024567</head>
<p>Coyote lived alone. He had no wife, but five children. He to them, "Stay here. I will go to see my friend the Mountain-Sheep." He went there. The Mountain-Sheep was lying holding a bow and five arrows. Coyote entered and sat Then the Mountain-Sheep got up and went out. He took the rows and shot up five times very quickly. Then he shot himself the anus five times, and ran away. Coyote sat watching. The <pb n=265>Mountain-Sheep came back with fat meat. He had intestine fat and good meat. He cooked some of it for Coyote. Coyote was hungry and ate it all. Then the Mountain-Sheep gave him the rest of the meat. Coyote tied it up and put it on his back. He said to the Mountain-Sheep: "Come to visit me to-morrow." The Mountain-Sheep said, "Yes." The next day he went there, following Coyote's tracks. He found Coyote's tent. He entered. Coyote was lying down just as the Mountain-Sheep had lain. He had Mountain-Sheep horns on his head, and he held five arrows and a bow. His children were not in the tent. He had sent them away. Then Coyote got up and went out. Just like the Mountain-Sheep, he took five arrows and shot them up, and then shot them into his anus. Only two entered; three times he missed, and the arrows stuck in his rump. Then he ran off. He came back carrying meat, with only one small piece of fat. He gave it to the Mountain-Sheep, "Here, my friend, eat this." The Mountain-Sheep said, "No, my friend, I do not like your meat. Eat it yourself. I will go back." He went away. "Yes," said Coyote. He was a little angry.</p>
<p>Coyote slept in his tent one night. The next day he said to his children, "Stay here. I will visit the Snowbird." Then he went. The Snowbird was lying down. He did not speak Coyote thought he was angry. Then the Snowbird went out. He came back carrying wood on his shoulder, and dropped it on the ground. "What does that mean?" thought Coyote. The Snowbird had a small door. He put the wood into this and took out nuts. Coyote was very hungry. He ate some and took the rest home for his children. He said: "Come to visit me." "Yes," said the Snowbird. The next day the Snowbird came. Coyote lay there. He did not look like Coyote, but like a Snowbird. He appeared angry. The Snowbird sat down, and Coyote went out. He came back again, carrying wood on his shoulder, and dropped it. He put the wood away and covered it from sight. When he took it out, it was nuts, but they were small and hard or hollow. He said, "Here, my friend, eat this." The Snowbird said, "No, I do not want it. Eat it yourself." "Yes," said Coyote. Then he ate the nuts himself.</p>
<p>Then Coyote said to his children, "Stay here, I will visit my friends." He went to the Magpie. The Magpie sat making a basket. Coyote sat down and watched him. The Magpie reached behind himself and took a little basket. He pushed a stick into his nostrils and made the blood run. Soon he had a basketful. He cooked the blood. He cut slices of fat and put them into the boiling blood. Then he gave it to Coyote. He ate it. It tasted good to him. He said, "My friend, you cook well. This is very good. like this kind of food. What do you think? Come to my house to <pb n=266>visit me." "Yes," said the Magpie. The next day the Magpie came. He sat down. Coyote was working, just as the Magpie had done. He used the same kind of awl. Slowly he reached backward and took a basket. He punched into his nostrils. Sometimes he hurt himself; then he sobbed or groaned. The Magpie looked at him and laughed. Coyote did not make much blood; the basket was only half full. Then he cooked the blood and put grease into it. He gave it to the Magpie. The Magpie said to him, "I do not like that. Eat it yourself." "Yes," said Coyote. Then he ate it himself.</p>
<p>Then Coyote said to his children, "Stay here, I will visit my friends." He went away. It was winter, and there was a little snow. He saw deer tracks, which were followed by other tracks. Coyote followed them both. He saw that some one had killed a deer, skinned it, butchered it, and carried the meat home. Coyote followed him. He saw the tent. There were three children and one woman. There was much dry meat, very good and fat. It was the tent of the Puma. He was not in the tent. He was hunting. The woman said to Coyote, "Are you hungry? Do you wish to eat?" Coyote said to her, "Yes, I am hungry." Then she cooked for him and gave him to eat. She said to him, "Stop! Wait! Sing while you eat. Do both together." Coyote said, "How shall I sing?" She said, "Wait. Listen. I will sing for you." Then she gave food to her children and sang. Then the children sang and ate, and Coyote sang and ate, until they had eaten all. Then she asked him, "Do you wish to go or to remain?" Coyote said, "I live far away. I think I will stay one night. I will go home to-morrow." At sunset the Puma came back. He had killed three deer. He carried one and dragged the two others, one in each hand. He laid them and entered the tent. He said to his wife, "I am hungry. Cook quickly. Coyote, my friend, is also hungry. Cook! I think Coyote does not eat meat." "Yes, I eat meat. I am hungry," Coyote. Then she cooked meat for them and set it down for them. The Puma said, "Now wait. Hear me. I will sing." Then he sang, and his children and Coyote too all sang, and then they ate, singing. They finished eating. Then they slept. Next morning the Puma told his wife to cook. Then she cooked and set out the food. They ate it just the same way, singing. Then the Puma said, "I am going to hunt now." Coyote said: "I will go back." Then the woman gave him two large bags of meat, and one small one. They were packed full. Coyote started. On the way he opened a sack. He ate while singing. He went on again. He stumbled and fell down. When he got up again, he had forgotten how to sing. He tried to sing, but forgot. He lost the song more <pb n=267>and more. Then he went back to the Puma's tent. He said, "I lost that song. I came back after it. Please give it to me again." "Yes," said Puma's wife. She sang it for him. Coyote went away, singing the song all day. At sunset, he arrived at his tent with his sacks. His children said, "Oh! Our father has meat." He said, "Wait! Cook it; then we will sing and eat." Then they sang and ate just as he had done before. After that he lost the song again, and again he obtained it from the Puma's wife. The Puma said to him, "If you lose the song you will see no game, and kill none, and you will have nothing to eat. Go back. Do not lose the song. Then hunt singing. You will find deer. If you do not sing, you will see nothing." Coyote sang all the way home.</p>
<p>One night he stayed there. Then he told his children, "Stay here, I will hunt." He went hunting, singing; then he saw deer tracks. He found the deer; singing, he went on. He came near them and killed five. He skinned them, no longer singing. He carried the meat home. Some of it he left, after having covered it. He got back. He entered his tent. He said to his daughters, "Do not eat of it. Cook for all together. Do not taste it. Do not let the children touch it. Then we will all sing and eat together." They cooked it and set it out. They all sat down. Coyote sang. Then all sang and ate. The next day Coyote said, "Stay here; I will go hunting." He went on the hills, but he saw nothing. Then he found many deer tracks. He sang. He killed all the deer; they were twenty. He looked at them. He saw a buck with eyes and a mouth, but without nostrils. Coyote said, "What kind of a deer is that? It is not good. It is bad. Where are its nostrils?" He looked at them all: they were all without nostrils. He took a stick and pushed it into the nose of one; then he pushed it in on the other side; thus, he made nostrils for it. Then he did the same to the rest. Deinde penem quasi ut nares amplificaret intromisit. Then the deer jumped, and ran away, and all the others ran away. Coyote seized his bow and shot one of them. He said, "What is the matter? It is not good to shoot deer by singing and then have them escape. It is good to pursue them and shoot them. I do not like the singing. I want to throw it away. I do not wish to sing any more." He skinned the deer, and carried the meat home. He said to his children, "Quick! Cook it." They cooked it and set it out. Coyote said, "Now we will eat. We will talk no more. I threw it away. We will not sing any more. We will only eat." They said to him, "Is that right? Will we eat without singing?" Coyote said to them, "Yes. It is right. We will sing no more. I threw it away."</p>
<p>Now the Puma went hunting. He found deer tracks. He saw <pb n=268>ten bucks. He went toward them, singing, singing. The sun was low. The Puma came to the windward of the deer. Then they smelled him, and ran away. He went home; he was angry. He thought Coyote had made this happen. He said to his wife, "I saw ten bucks. I sang, but I did not kill them. I went around them; then they smelled me and ran away. I think Coyote made nostrils for them and caused them to smell. I am angry. I will hunt again. I want to find out about Coyote. I wish to find out if he did it." The Puma went off; he found tracks and saw deer. He came near them. He was going around them; suddenly they ran away. Then he was angry. He thought Coyote was the cause. He went home empty-handed and angry. At sunset he started to go to Coyote. When he came near, he said, "Let Coyote sleep well. Let him not awaken. Let it be the same with all his children." He went into Coyote's tent. Coyote was sleeping. Puma pulled his nose and his tail and his legs. He made his long and thin, so that they had no flesh on them. Then he his ears straight up. In the morning, Coyote got up. He saw nose; he saw his long legs and his tail. He awoke his children, being frightened. "Is that you, my father?" they said. "Yes," Coyote. "You do not look like him. I think you are a bad said they. Coyote said, "No, I am your father; perhaps Puma did this to me. He made me sleep. Perhaps he was angry that I did not sing. I also am angry; I will do it to him At night he went to the Puma. When he was close, he said, him be sleepy. Let him not awake." He entered the tent. pushed the Puma's nose in. He crushed his legs and his claws, that they were compressed. He pulled his tail long. He short little ears for him. Then Coyote went home. Then Puma awoke in the morning. He said to his wife, "Give me water." she gave it to him. He was washing. In rubbing down over face his hand slipped [not being stopped by the projecting nose formerly]. He said, "What is the matter with my face?" daughter said to him, "You are not my father. You are a man. I am afraid of you." The Puma said, "Yes, I am he. What is the matter with my face?" She said, "It is not good." Then the Puma said, "I think Coyote did it. I did the same to him night."</p>
</body>