<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB_XML/main/Schema/FFDB_mini.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB_XML/main/Schema/FFDB_mini.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<body>
<head>NNA026124</head>
<p>A young woman used to dress like a man. She and Grasshopper were hunting-partners, but Grasshopper did not know that she was a woman. She killed plenty of game, while Grasshopper did not kill anything. He wondered why she was such a good hunter, and also why she always sat down when she wanted to urinate. One day they came to a porcupine-den, and she sat down to urinate. Grasshopper ran through the porcupine-den, and, coming out close behind her, put his hand below her, and found out that she was a woman. The woman was ashamed, and went home and told her parents. They ranged up all the men, and had them pass before the girl, to find out who had done it.<note>See BBAE 59 : 287 (note 2).</note> Grasshopper sat in the corner, laughing. All the men passed in view, but the girl could not point to any of them. Then she looked around, and, seeing Grasshopper sitting in the corner, pointed him out as the culprit. The girl's father gave him the girl for his wife. Now they went out on a hunting-trip together. Grasshopper, being the husband, went out hunting every day, but never killed anything except other grasshoppers. He ate only grasshoppers and sinew of game. He ate no flesh of any kind. They were starving, and the woman herself had to go out hunting. After a time a baby was born. One day when they moved camp, Grasshopper, who was unable to carry much weight, went ahead with the baby, while <pb n="237"/>his wife followed with a heavy load of camp-outfit. Grasshopper grew tired carrying the baby. He choked it, and hung it up on a tree. Then he went off hunting grasshoppers. At night, when he came to camp, he found his wife crying. He said to her, "Grasshopper, Grasshopper-Child<note>It is said that he always addressed his wife and child thus.</note> is not dead. Why do you cry? He struck the baby with his mitts, and it woke up, as though it had only been asleep. His wife was glad, and said to him, "Kill a bear for me to-morrow." Grasshopper went out, and, while hunting grasshoppers in the grass, saw a huge monster approach. He was too late to get away, and the monster swallowed him. He tried to get out, and at last emerged through the anus. In this way the animal was killed. He went home, and said to his wife, "I have killed a bear for you. I jumped down his mouth, passed through all his insides, then came out and shot him."<note>See RBAE 31 : 718, 868.</note> She went out to see; and when she saw the huge carcass, she fell down from fright and crawled away, for her legs trembled so that she could not walk. Grasshopper came; and when he tapped her on the legs with his mitts, she became well, and walked back to camp. She said to him, "Bears are not like that: they are black, and only a little larger than a dog." He went out hunting, and this time he killed a bear. His wife sent him to her mother. He went, and staid some time. His mother-in-law gave him plenty of meat to eat, but this was not his food. He wanted sinew to eat. He became so weak and sick that he had to crawl on his way back to his wife. He said to her, "Your mother gave me nothing but her excrements to eat, and made me sick." They moved camp again, this time to snare caribou. Grasshopper said to his wife, "Use me as a trigger for the snare [like the trigger of a rabbit-snare]." His wife chased a caribou into the snare. The caribou went with great force and cut Grasshopper in two. He said to his wife, "Quick! put me together [join my legs to my body], that I may chase the caribou." In her haste she joined the two parts of his body the wrong way; so that, when he ran forward, he was looking backwards. He was angry and ran off, but he could not go straight. He called to her, "Quick! break me, and join me again! " She broke him and joined him again, and now he went straight ahead. He said to her, "When you see smoke, you will know that I have overtaken and killed the caribou." His wife saw smoke in a far-away mountain, and went there.<note>My informant thought there was more to this story, but he had forgotten it.</note></p>
</body>