<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB_XML/main/Schema/FFDB_mini.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB_XML/main/Schema/FFDB_mini.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<body>
<head>NNA026106</head>
<p>A young man lived with his uncle, who made many arrows for him. The youth always shot them away, and came back from hunting without arrows or game. His uncle thought he would watch him. He saw some caribou running away from the youth, who ran after them just a little way. Then he walked with long strides to make people think that he had been running. His uncle then ran ahead, killed all the caribou, and waited for the youth to come up. He was walking comfortably. His uncle asked him why he was not running, and said, "You will never catch any game in that way. Caribou run fast." The youth answered, "When I run a short time, my heart begins to beat so hard, that I become afraid and have to walk." They carried the meat to camp. Now the youth's uncle took him hunting sheep, and killed several. He made his nephew carry a whole sheep up a steep mountain. He made him run. At first he ran, and then he walked. His uncle followed close behind, and pushed him when he went too slowly. The youth nearly dropped, but his uncle made him go to the top without stopping. Then his uncle said to him, "You will not die. You will never be out of breath." The next day he took him to a sweat-house, in which he made much steam. The youth tried to run out, saying that his heart was sick and that he was going to die. His uncle said to him, "You cannot get out until the sweat-house begins to cool off," and he held him down. Thus he trained him in the sweat-house and by making him run and climb steep slopes until he could do those things like other people. In the end he became a great hunter.</p>
</body>