<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB_XML/main/Schema/FFDB_mini.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB_XML/main/Schema/FFDB_mini.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<body>
<head>NSA010283</head>
<p>The elder Yoálox was particularly fond of sea lion fat and whale oil; they tasted very good to him and he craved this food. He was very careful always to have a large supply of whale oil on hand. One day he considered a plan to turn into whale oil and sea lion fat the water in all the channels, streams, and lagoons. But this enormous mass was always to remain fresh, never to turn bad, never to lose its good flavor, and never to run out. He said to himself: "If it were arranged <pb n="41"/>that way, the people would always have fresh whale oil on hand; they could save themselves dangerous journeys and strenuous hunts; they would never have to do without these delicacies, and life would be a good deal more pleasant!"</p>
<p>He then put this plan before his younger brother and tried to win him over. The latter, however, wanted nothing to do with it and put his brother down: "It must never be as you plan. People must be obliged to work always. Men have to go hunting. When they have killed sea lions or whales the women will prepare the blubber; then all may greatly enjoy the delicious whale oil which only tastes good after strenuous work. People must not be granted pleasure without work!"</p>
<p>Thus once again the elder Yoálox had to abandon his plan and yield to the decision of his younger brother. Soon afterward the elder Yoálox undertook a long journey on foot during which he became very tired and hungry. He sat down on a stone to rest a while. The earth was very swampy, however, and water soon oozed up around his feet. Since he was hungry, the thought occurred to him: "How good it would be if all the water that rises up wherever I or anyone else puts his foot should instantly turn into whale oil. Everybody would have more than enough with which to appease his hunger!" This wish, too, he soon put before his younger brother. Displeased, the latter said: "It must never come to that! May people go hungry if they don't work!" This made the elder Yoálox sad again, and his wish has not been realized. It is because of this that from that time on it has become an inescapable rule for men to go hunting and for all people to worry about getting food. On numerous occasions the attitude of the younger Yoálox quite clearly reveals how younger brothers or sisters are frequently wiser and more prudent, but also more stubborn, than their older siblings.</p>
</body>