<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB_XML/main/Schema/FFDB_mini.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB_XML/main/Schema/FFDB_mini.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<body>
<head>NSA010274</head>
<p>Once in the old days when spring was approaching a man looked out of his hut and saw a bandurria<note>The sturdy, rusty brown, spectacled ibis, Theristicus melanopis, bears this name in Argentina and Chile. See also narrative 7 in this volume.</note> fly overhead. He was so happy about <pb n="26"/>it that he called over to the other huts: "A bandurria is flying over my hut. Look!" Hearing this the others rushed out of their huts shouting loudly: "Spring is here again. The ibises are flying already!" They jumped for joy and talked loudly.</p>
<p>Léxuwa, however, is a very delicate and sensitive woman: she wants to be treated with special deference. She heard the noise of the screaming men, women, and children, and became very angry. Deeply offended she called forth a sudden heavy snowstorm, accompanied by strong frost and lots of ice. From then on snow kept falling and falling for months on end. Snow fell incessantly and as it was extremely cold, the whole earth became covered with ice. The water froze in all the waterways. Many, many people died because they could not get into their canoes to gather food. They were unable even to leave their huts in order to collect firewood, for there was deep snow everywhere. More and more people died.</p>
<p>At long last it ceased snowing, and soon the sun began shining brightly. It burned so fiercely that it melted the ice and snow that had covered the earth to the highest mountaintops. Then much water came flowing down into the channels and into the sea. The sun was so hot that the mountaintops were scorched. They have remained bare to this day. The ice covering the wide and narrow waterways also melted. At last the people were able to get to the beach again and into their canoes to look for food. Only on the vast mountain slopes and in the deep valleys has the thick ice remained until today. Here it was too thick even for that sun to melt it. One can still see this enormous mass of ice lying there; it even reaches down into the sea,<note>This obviously refers to the big glaciers that dot principally the northwestern arm of the Beagle Channel in considerable numbers (Gusinde 1937:12).</note> so thick was the mantle of ice that then enveloped the whole earth. At that time there was an extraordinarily severe frost, and a fearsome amount of snow had fallen. All this had been caused by Léxuwakipa; she is a very delicate, sensitive woman.</p>
<p>Since then the Yamana treat the bandurria with utmost respect. When she approaches their huts, the people remain silent and quiet; especially the little children are kept still and prevented from screaming.</p>
</body>