<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB_XML/main/Schema/FFDB_mini.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB_XML/main/Schema/FFDB_mini.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<body>
<head>NSA010311</head>
<p>For some time Ašóulaxipa<note>The female small grampus, also called springer, Pseudarca crassidens.</note> had not loved her husband; she had grown tired of him. Therefore she liked to go out on the ocean alone in <pb n="126"/>her canoe, where she would spend a long time fishing. She always took her younger son along with her, leaving the elder son behind in the hut with his father.</p>
<p>Whenever she got close to a lakúma the cunning woman said to him from her canoe: "Oh, how nice; there I see my dear grandfather again!" Whereupon the lakúma let her continue unmolested and did her no harm. When she continued paddling and met another lakúma she called to this one, too, in a friendly tone: "Oh, how nice; there I see my dear grandfather again!" That way this one, too, let the woman continue without doing her any harm. This is how Ašóulaxipa saved herself every time. But many other women were dragged out of their canoes by the lakúma and pulled to the bottom of the sea.</p>
<p>Once a whale had stranded on a nearby island. Ašóulaxipa went there with her canoe to get some oil. As soon as her canoe touched shore she let her young son get out. But the rocky beach was completely covered with oil and was so slippery that the boy kept losing his footing. Ašóulaxipa called out in a loud voice: "Listen, you, don't let my little son slip all the time! He keeps falling and falling." There was, indeed, a man living on the island whom she secretly loved and for whom this was intended. She called in this sly way to lure him out. Soon the man came to the beach. When he saw Ašóulaxipa, he liked her very much. The two fell in love at first sight. The man said to her: "Stay with me on this island. You can be my wife." Ašóulaxipa was very pleased with this proposal and secretly rejoiced. She answered: "All right, I'll be your wife. But first let me get my elder son; he's staying with his father in the hut!" She hurried back to her hut, but did not make her intentions known. The moment no one was looking she put her elder son in the canoe and went away with him. Soon they reached the island again. Since then Ašóulaxipa has lived with that man on the island, having left her first husband forever.<note>What is so important in this story is the reference to the behavior of the Yamana toward a lakúma, which they greatly fear. It is considered to be a sea monster that endangers every canoe and pulls the passengers down into the sea. This evil water-spirit is described in more detail below (Gusinde 1937:1285-1286).</note></p>
</body>