<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB_XML/main/Schema/FFDB_mini.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB_XML/main/Schema/FFDB_mini.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<body>
<head>NSA010286</head>
<p>Since then the younger Yoálox lived alone with Mákuxipa, who had become his wife. He slept with her, and she became pregnant. Eventually she gave birth to a son.<note>The particular aim of this story is to demonstrate that both conception and childbirth, as both processes occur since then, were introduced for the first time through Yoálox. According to this, children previously had not been actually "born," and nowhere is it explained in what manner they came into existence. All the people of the "first times" are simply presented as adults. But from now on starts the process of growing up in the way characteristic of human beings.</note> Yoálox was immensely pleased. At once <pb n="48"/>he informed his wife in detail about what to do in childbirth and how to behave during the time immediately following it. All Yamana women still follow these instructions.</p>
<p>Yoálox's first child was a boy. He cried incessantly, most loudly during the night. He never stopped screaming; his mother and father tried everything possible to make him stop but to no avail. Yoálox looked highly displeased; since the mother had to go about her work, it was impossible for her to stay constantly with the child.</p>
<p>Very annoyed, Yoálox finally ran out of his hut, leaving the boy alone. At some distance away he built himself another hut. He went hunting as regularly as before and continued working on his weapons. But whenever he approached the huts, be it from the forest or from the beach, he could hear his son's loud crying from afar. When he stepped into his hut nearby the boy yelled even louder. He continued to cry incessantly, even when Yoálox made noises to make him be quiet.</p>
<p>Sulkily one day he again entered the hut where his little son was lying. With both hands he grabbed him under his armpits, lifted him up, stared sharply into his face, and roared: "Will you stop screaming!" This very instant the little boy split right down the middle, so that Yoálox now had two sons. They did not cry, though. They were the first humans.<note>These words mean: those two children are the first who were brought into the world by actual birth. Strictly according to the wording, however, this applies to only one of them.</note></p>
<p>After some time Mákuxipa died. Since the younger Yoálox was always occupied he could not be busy watching his two sons. He looked for a woman to take care of his two boys and chose Čilawáiakipa [vixen]. Right away she moved into Yoálox's hut and devoted herself to his two sons. Now Yoálox could even go on long journeys without worrying.</p>
<p>The vixen named the two boys Šamanáuye. She was very clever and cunning, and was soon scheming to roast and eat the boys. Yoálox was very far away at the time; before he came back she could be gone and hiding in the woods. So now she wanted to carry out her plan. She told the two boys: "Go into the forest and collect plenty of dry wood! Bring it quickly back here to the hut; we are going to start a big fire!" The two boys ran into the forest. But Čilawáiakipa had treated them badly from the start. She had made them work very hard, and the two were angry at her. At last they wanted to avenge themselves. Instead of collecting dry wood they gathered green and wet sticks and carried them to the hut. The vixen tried to light a big fire with it but was not able to do so. Angrily, she scolded the boys: "You've brought me green <pb n="49"/>and wet wood; it's impossible to light a big fire with that!" The following day she again sent the two boys into the forest to collect dry wood. But this time, again, they gathered only green, wet wood and carried it to the hut. They had noticed that the vixen was planning something evil. Yet they did not know how to cope with the difficult situation, for their father was far away on the other side of the channel. They had long since tired of having to stay constantly with ill-humored, stingy Čilawáiakipa who, in addition to sending them into the forest for wood, burdened them daily with lots of work. Deliberately they now gathered only wet wood. This made the vixen furious each time and she took her ill humor out on them in every conceivable way. The two boys suffered much unpleasantness.</p>
<p>One day Čilawáiakipa was lying on her bed fast asleep. Quickly the two boys lit a big fire<note>What is meant is an actual signal fire, customary among the Yamana (Gusinde 1937:1020).</note> to signal a canoe. And indeed, soon a man appeared on the beach. The boys stepped swiftly into his canoe and begged to be taken to the other shore. This the man did, and the two boys disembarked on the opposite side. They continued running in the direction where they supposed their father to be. Unexpectedly they came to a wide river; they did not know how to cross it since it was very wide. They feared now the vixen might come after them. But Yoálox, their father, had seen them come running from afar; he knew that they were right then standing at the wide river, not knowing what to do. So he quickly drained the water in the river, and his two sons reached the other shore without effort. Soon they came to the place where Yoálox was sitting. He asked them: "Why are you following me; what has brought you here?" Tearfully the two sons now told their father how badly they were treated by Čilawáiakipa, how hard they had to work, how they were sent into the forest every day to collect dry wood, and that they got very little to eat. To this they added: "We had hardly stepped into that man's canoe and reached the middle of the channel when we looked back to see Čilawáiakipa throw herself over Mákuxipa's dead body and eat of it! She was surely planning to eat us, too. That's why she sent us into the forest every day to collect piles of dry wood for a fire over which she intended to roast us!"</p>
<p>The younger Yoálox became very angry at this. Full of rage he quickly made a yékuš. This he hurled at Čilawáiakipa so that she fell dead on the spot. From then on the two boys stayed with their father; they had grown up in the meantime.<note>In this story are repeated several details of what the Selknam tell about Kwányip's two nephews (Gusinde 1931:595).</note></p>
<p><pb n="50"/>But since that time one can occasionally see the fox dig up human corpses and eat of them. It is a disgusting animal.</p>
</body>