<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB_XML/main/Schema/FFDB_mini.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB_XML/main/Schema/FFDB_mini.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<body>
<head>NSA010330</head>
<p>A girl who is túri is not allowed to eat berries. Now once there was a túrikipa who felt very much like eating berries. She secretly ran away, sat down in the forest, and ate lots of amáim. Actually the girl did not eat and swallow the berries; she only put them into her mouth, squeezed out the juice with her teeth, and threw the solid parts away.<note>In this way the girl thought she would be able to get around the wording of the unequivocal and definite prohibition.</note> None of her family knew about this.</p>
<p>When soon afterward the family of this túrikipa was crossing a wide waterway a big lakúma emerged and threatened the people. In their fear they promptly threw many mussels, birds, and chunks of meat into the water, but the lakúma did not let go of the canoe. The girl kept herself hidden on the bottom of the canoe, not looking up once. The people threw their dog overboard but the lakúma was not satisfied with that, either. In their despair the people hurled a small girl into the water; the girl sank very quickly. Still the lakúma did not release the canoe. Finally the people pushed that big girl, the túrikipa, overboard. The lakúma seized her eagerly and dived with her as quickly as lightning. Soon the entrails [of that girl] surfaced. This made the people very sad. Before long the lakúma itself appeared on the surface again, laid itself flat, and became very wide. Then the people discovered on its back a large number of mussels, of a size bigger than they had ever seen before.<note>It is known that on the back of an old whale there are numerous parasites, mainly of the Balanus and Coropula types. This passage refers to them.</note> The men reached for them and got a few. Their shells were particularly sharp. In their fury the men quickly cut up the lakúma with them, ripped out its entrails, and dismembered it completely. The lakúma died immediately and sank to the bottom of the sea. In that instant and without anyone paddling the canoe moved from the spot, and soon reached shore. The people breathed a sigh of relief. But the girl was lost, for she had eaten of the berries when túrikipa.</p>
</body>