<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB_XML/main/Schema/FFDB_mini.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB_XML/main/Schema/FFDB_mini.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<body>
<head>NSA010320</head>
<p>A long time ago an unusually severe winter set in; lots of snow fell and it was icy cold. Worst hit were the Wollaston Islands where snow piled up high and remained for a long time. Isolated there on an island sat a woman who had been alone for quite some time. She no longer had fire, for there were no šewáli [firestones] left. She also had hardly anything left to eat. So she found herself in great distress, for the long winter was extremely severe. One night she was lying on her bed still awake, when she saw a big black bird enter her hut and sit down in the middle of it. Soon it began to talk exactly like a Yamana. The woman listened closely and assured herself that the bird was really speaking her own language. Amazed, she said to herself: "But how is that possible? <pb n="152"/>That bird speaks just like the Yamana. Isn't that strange!" Unnoticed she lifted her head a bit. She discovered a great number of these birds in the middle of her hut; they were sitting around the fire which they themselves had lit again, warming themselves. They were all shivering with cold in the frosty air. The woman drew up a bit closer behind the birds, where it was very dark since they themselves were obscuring the light from the flames. That is how close they were to the fire. Now the woman could understand exactly what these birds were saying. Indeed, all spoke just like Yamana, and Marutuwérelakípa<note>This name identifies a sea bird of average size. I was not able to determine the species zoologically as the Indians were unable to describe it clearly enough. This type of bird appears also in the next two stories.</note> caught every word clearly. Each bird spoke of its long journeys far out on the open sea, of the harbors it visited, of the rocks and islands it had flown by, of the animals it had hunted down, of the many dangers it had escaped. Meanwhile all were warming themselves comfortably by the fire. The woman was listening attentively. Since the birds spoke just like Yamana she believed everything they said. She was keeping herself in deep shadow and all the birds had their backs to her. She was so extremely happy and pleased, and finally convinced herself that those birds had to be people after all. She gave a sigh of relief and said to herself: "How nice that at last some of my people have come here. Now I'm no longer so completely alone!" Then she moved even closer to sit in the circle of birds; she wanted to tell them how long she had been sitting here alone and how much she wanted to warm herself by the fire she had been without for so long. But as she was pushing herself into the circle of birds to sit down she bumped her arm against one of them. She just had time to see that all the birds were scraping and cleaning skins. The woman was now brightly illuminated by the flames, and when the birds spotted her in their midst they became very frightened. They rose quickly, extinguished the fire, snatched up all their skins, and flew away. Only a whale was left behind; it was too heavy for them. The startled woman followed the birds with her eyes. But they were gone. Now she no longer doubted that all those creatures really were birds, namely touwíšiwa.<note>The iridescent cormorant, Phalacrocorax olivaceus.</note> She saw the big whale which the birds had left for her, and thus did not have to die of hunger. But still she was very sad that she was all by herself again on the island and without fire. She cried for a long, long time. Then she, too, turned into a bird, the marutuwérelakípa out there on the open sea.</p>
</body>