<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB_XML/main/Schema/FFDB_mini.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB_XML/main/Schema/FFDB_mini.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<body>
<head>NSA010317</head>
<p>Once there was a bachelor. He proved himself to be very skillful at catching fish, always bringing home many big ones. In the same camp there lived another man who was married to a beautiful woman. He had no luck at all at fishing. One day he asked the bachelor: "Where do you catch all these big fish?" The bachelor answered: "I always find them over there by that island!" The married man asked: "Would you take me there some time?" The bachelor immediately replied: "Come on!" And the two went to the island. First they ran along the beach until they were standing opposite the island, which was a great distance away. Indeed one could see on this island a lot of fish entrails, small balls of grass with which the insides of the fish had been cleaned, and also well sharpened mussel shells with which the bellies of the fish had been cut open.<note>As is well known every man cleans and dresses the larger animals immediately on the spot where he caught and killed them.</note> The married man asked: "You told me you could reach this island with one single jump. But it's too far away! I couldn't reach it in one jump!" The bachelor replied with a laugh: "It only looks <pb n="148"/>as though the island is far off; actually it is quite close. If you get a good running start you can easily jump across. You'll certainly reach the island. Be brave!" Upon hearing these words the other actually started running, intending to jump. He came running bravely but in the end he stopped short. He stopped suddenly and did not jump. Then the bachelor urged him even more: "Come on, don't be frightened! The island is really not as far away as it seems. Just try once more!" The other tried again; he started running very fast and from far away and actually jumped. But the island was too distant after all: the man fell into the water and hit his head against a rock, killing himself instantly. "Now you can get fish, as many and as big ones as you'd like!" said the bachelor, laughing mockingly. Then he added: "You may stay there forever!" He left the dead man lying in the water and went contentedly to the latter's hut. The wife was sitting by the fire. Joyfully the bachelor told her that her husband after smashing his head near the island had died on the spot. Both burst out laughing with delight. They had secretly been lovers for a long time. Now at last the husband was dead. They caressed each other and indulged in their desire. Late at night the woman's eldest son came back to the hut. He had approached it very quietly. But when he entered unexpectedly and saw his mother lying next to the bachelor, he became furious. He drove the harpoon he was holding through the bachelor's body, just punishment for the culprit.<note>This story is told in the south. Its structure resembles that of the following story which is told in the west.</note></p>
</body>