<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB_XML/main/Schema/FFDB_mini.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB_XML/main/Schema/FFDB_mini.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<body>
<head>NSA010331</head>
<p>Once a hánnuš fell in love with Maxutuwérelakipa. She was an extraordinarily beautiful woman, and cunning and sly besides. For her part, she wanted nothing to do with the hánnuš and drove him away whenever he drew close to caress her. At first he was disappointed, but later it annoyed him very much to have gone so often and in vain to Maxutuwérelakipa's hut. Finally he threatened to kill her if she did not yield to him.</p>
<p>This woman lived on an island. It was winter then. When the hánnuš threatened he would soon return with many other hánnuš to finish her off she thought seriously of defending herself. She hastened to build a sturdy hut for herself and covered it with strong pieces of bark. She kept the entrance particularly low and narrow. Opposite the entrance she left a hole and placed some brushwood in front of it, so that nobody would notice it. She knew how to make fine and solid sírsa [forks to catch crabs with]; she always had a supply of them.</p>
<p>One evening the hánnuš showed up at the woman's place again bringing several companions along. She was well prepared, however. Upon seeing the hánnuš coming toward her hut, which was covered <pb n="180"/>with large pieces of bark, she quickly crawled outside through the narrow opening in the back. When the hánnuš entered he could not find her. He turned toward the entrance and looked out. While he was bending over to ease himself through the door the woman stood up in her hiding place and thrust a crab fork vigorously into his backside. The hánnuš gave a loud scream of pain and scurried out through the narrow entrance. Immediately another hánnuš squeezed himself into the hut to see what had happened. But he did not find Maxutuwérelakipa, either. As he likewise bent over to crawl out, the woman, with a powerful thrust, drove a sírsa also into his backside. He could not help screaming loudly and with the sírsa sticking in his behind he instantly squeezed out through the narrow entrance. The rest of the hánnuš were amazed at this. Still a third ventured into the hut, looked around for the woman, and was just as unable as the others to find her. He went to the entrance and from within called to the other hánnuš: "I can't find the woman here!" As he bent down to exit Maxutuwérelakipa from her hiding place drove a crab fork into his backside, too. He could hardly move on account of the pain, so deeply had the sírsa penetrated. Yet he forced himself, dragging the sírsa stuck in his behind until one of the other hánnuš could free him from it. He was screaming terribly. The rest of the hánnuš were very uneasy. They conferred with one another and decided: "We had better get away from here quickly, all of us!" So they got up and hurried back into the heart of the forest.</p>
<p>Cunning Maxutuwérelakipa over there on the island had long since carried all her things to another place on the beach. When the hánnuš were far enough away she crawled out of her hiding place and hurried down to the beach. It was a harsh winter and the channel was frozen over. She stepped on the thick ice cover and found it resistant. But as she advanced the ice cracked behind her. By the time she had reached the middle of the channel the fleeing hánnuš reached the top of a nearby mountain. From there they saw Maxutuwérelakipa. They became furious and rushed down from the mountain to the beach in order to kill that miserable woman who had outwitted them all. But Maxutuwérelakipa called jeeringly to the hánnuš: "Just come after me, while I wait for you here!" The first hánnuš ran out on the ice thinking that it was still the large, continuous cover of solid immovable ice over which the woman had advanced. But since she had broken up the compact sheet into small cakes of ice those first hánnuš immediately went under. The small ice floes could not carry the big, heavy creatures. When the other hánnuš on the shore saw the first ones drown they stayed behind; they hurled many threats at Maxutuwérelakipa and then turned back.</p>
</body>