<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB_XML/main/Schema/FFDB_mini.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB_XML/main/Schema/FFDB_mini.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<body>
<head>NSA010326</head>
<p>Once several families had a camp, and among them there lived two unpopular men. It was not long before the two noticed that the others were planning to kill them. So they left, quickly and secretly. Eventually the people noticed that they were gone; they pursued them in the hope of catching them again. But the two men were already far away; they had run quickly. Unexpectedly they came to Kaluwéllawaia, a narrow inlet which cuts deeply into the coast [in the west]. It was impossible to go around it because its shores were steep and covered with dense vegetation; nor was there a crossing [fjord] that they could have used. Strangely, though, there were many big fish in the water, pressed closely together with their backs slightly above the surface. In their distress the two men set out to walk across on these fish, first one, then the other. The first walked over the fish with great caution; he reached the other shore and then jumped onto a cliff; he was saved. But the second man trod with less caution so that one of the fish moved; he slipped, fell, sank down into the water, and was eaten alive by the big fish. His companion saw this from the shore and became very sad. But he had to hurry along and soon he came to Aniawáia [bay east of Puerto Olla]. Here he found a large camp where many people had erected their huts. He told them how the people in the other camp had intended to kill him, how he had run away, how he had saved himself in Kaluwéllawaia, and how his friend had slipped and been eaten alive by the big fish. When the people heard this they became very sad and promptly began their yamalašemóina. For a long time they painted themselves, as they always do when they are in mourning. They also decided to make many yékus with which to kill those big fish.</p>
<p><pb n="169"/>One day when their mourning ceremony had come to a close, several men and a woman got into a canoe to go where certain stones can be found that are used for making points. They paddled all day long and did not reach the place until evening. They disembarked. The men rapidly built a hut and the woman gathered mussels on the beach. Then all sat down by the fire and ate a lot, because the men had to fortify themselves for the job that lay ahead.</p>
<p>The following morning they got up early. But before they went into the forest they said to the woman: "You get into the canoe and go far out on the channel; tie it to seaweed and stay there until we get back to the beach. For here in this region lives a man who is as handsome as máku;<note>Here again the reference is to the scarlet flower of the Embothrium coccineum shrub; cf. Gusinde 1937:702, fig. 78.</note> he is so handsome that he might easily ensnare you! Therefore you had better go out on the channel and stay there to avoid becoming seduced by this good-looking man." The woman was very serious and strong-willed; she had never had anything to do with other men, nor did she show any inclination for this. Therefore she replied: "I'll do everything you told me!"</p>
<p>When the men had once more eaten their fill, they went into the forest and climbed the mountain. They got to the place where the suitable stone is found and promptly made stone points. From up there they often looked down to the channel where they saw the canoe far from the beach tied to seaweed; the woman was sitting inside. Reassured they said: "Just look at that! She's a good, serious woman; that handsome Hulušénuwa<note>The smaller of the two species of wren in Tierra del Fuego, Troglodytes hornensis (Gusinde 1937:42). It plays a part also in narrative 17 of this volume.</note> won't get anywhere with her!"</p>
<p>Indeed, Hulušénuwa soon did come to the beach; he really was as good-looking as máku. Seeing the woman sitting there in the canoe alone he beckoned her to come ashore, intent on having intimate relations with her. He enticed her for a long time with flattering words. The woman looked at him frequently and noticed more clearly how wonderfully handsome this man Hulušénuwa was. She heard his alluring calls and felt more and more attracted to him: he was exceedingly handsome and enticed her very seductively with sweet words. But in spite of all this the woman controlled herself; she remained steadfast in her canoe and did not untie it from the [Macrocystis] seaweed.</p>
<p>Toward evening the men came down from the mountain and approached the beach. Handsome Hulušénuwa noticed them and hid in the forest. The men came out of the forest and called the woman. She <pb n="170"/>untied the canoe and came paddling toward shore. The men loaded all the yékuš on board; they had brought very many. Then they themselves got in and returned to the camp. When they arrived the woman went to the other women and told them what had happened to her. She said: "Where we were today there lives an extremely handsome man, he is as handsome as máku! He can charm every single one of us women, that's how magnificent he is. He greatly attracted me, too. I felt a strong desire to yield to him. But I made a big effort and did not give in to my desire. In fact I remained in the canoe far out on the channel. None of you could do that, for this man is exceedingly good-looking!" All the women listened very attentively. Then they said laughingly: "We could manage that, too, just like you!" Another woman said loudly: "Me he couldn't seduce under any circumstances. I wouldn't let myself be ensnared by him!" Her own husband heard that. So he told her: "All right, why don't you go with us tomorrow; then we'll see how you behave!"</p>
<p>The following day the men went out again, this time taking that other woman along. They got to the well-known place and disembarked. The men quickly built a hut and the woman looked for mussels which they roasted over the fire; they ate, giving themselves strength. But before they went into the forest the husband said to his wife: "Now you must get into the canoe and go far out on the channel. Tie the canoe to a bunch of seaweed and remain there until we come back. We'll call you when you can come paddling back to the shore!" The woman replied: "All right, I'll leave at once!" The men hurried into the forest and climbed the mountain.</p>
<p>But the woman remained on the beach for some time, undoubtedly waiting for that handsome man. And indeed Hulušénuwa soon arrived. The woman was captivated just by looking at him. She ran toward him and threw herself into his arms. She forced him down on the sand and here they yielded long to their lust. Meanwhile the men had long since reached the place where the stones for the yékuš are, and here they were busily working away. Although they looked down from time to time across the wide waterway they could not see the canoe. Repeatedly they told one another: "There we are! The canoe is most likely still lying by the shore. That's probably how it is: that woman has let herself be tempted by Hulušénuwa, and the two are now having fun together on the beach." After some time the men went down the mountain and soon reached the beach. Here they saw the evil doings of the two who were still embracing each other, lying on the beach. When Hulušénuwa noticed the approaching men he ran away in a great hurry. But the woman remained lying there, totally out of her senses <pb n="171"/>with desire. When her own husband got there he kicked her. Only then did she recognize him and said: "Cool me off, for I'm still full of desire. Hulusénuwa is so wonderfully handsome that I am beside myself!" The man walked some distance away and heated a sharp stone point. With this he quickly returned to where his wife was lying. With all his strength he pushed this red hot stone point into her vagina and slit open her stomach to the navel. In this condition he left her. He was boiling with rage.</p>
<p>The men got into the canoe without the woman and returned to the camp where the women were waiting on the beach. They saw that there were only men sitting in the canoe and asked: "What? Are only the men coming back? Where can the woman be? Aha! She must have let herself be seduced by that handsome man; she yielded to him and stayed behind with him. So then she did let herself be tempted by him, after all!" The men disembarked. They said that the woman had let herself be ensnared by that man out there and that she had died from wanton lust. But they did not mention that her furious husband had slit her stomach open.</p>
<p>The following day the men went back to that place for they needed still more yékuš. But the woman whom they had left behind the day before was no longer there: handsome Hulusénuwa, who is himself a clever yékamus, had completely cured and taken her for his wife. Since then both live together amusing themselves with each other.</p>
</body>