<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB_XML/main/Schema/FFDB_mini.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB_XML/main/Schema/FFDB_mini.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<body>
<head>NSA010271</head>
<p>Lem was an excellent person who had a strong influence over all the men. They willingly submitted to him because he behaved in a friendly and benevolent manner toward everybody. He was so handsome and so beautifully built that every woman wished to stare at him all the time. But each kept from revealing her desire, refraining even from looking at him openly, for fear the others might make fun of her. Lem was delightful. The women were all in love with him; the men regarded him highly.</p>
<p><pb n="20"/>Lem's wife was also very beautiful. Nobody knows her name. Lem had several pretty daughters, like the seagull Tákaša [Larus belcheri], the seagull Wémarkipa [Larus glaucodes], the sea duck Wiyen [Anas cristata], the seagull Kiwágu [Larus dominicanus], the Magellanic goose, Kímoa [Chloephaga picta], the duck Wípatux [Querquedula cyanoptera], the vixen Čilawáiakipa [Canis magellanicus], and the rat Wésana. The latter two secretly carried off the meat their father brought home from the hunt, robbing him regularly. They carry on this [stealing] even today. Besides them, Lem had several other daughters. He also had a number of sons. One of them is Yéxalem, who constantly follows his father about.</p>
<p>Lem was diligent and hard-working, kind, always cheerful, and friendly toward everyone. He was on the best of terms with all the men, and a model of an active and congenial person. To this day nothing in this [that is to say, in his basic personality] has changed. At the time of the great uprising in Yáiaašága he helped the men decisively to seize the women's kína. After the upheaval was over he went up to the sky. There he is still good-natured and ready to help the people by giving much light and warmth to everybody. All the men are openly proud of him, for he uncovered the secret of the women's kína and in so doing freed them from female domination.</p>
<p>Actually there is yet another world. That is why Lem leaves the land of the Yamana every evening to go there. In that other world, too, he furnishes sufficient light and warmth. Then, the next morning he comes back to us again. In this way he helps the people there as well as here.</p>
</body>