<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB_XML/main/Schema/FFDB_mini.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB_XML/main/Schema/FFDB_mini.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<body>
<head>NSA010281</head>
<p>Both Yoálox were highly skilled craftsmen. After all, in the course of their long wanderings throughout the world they had come to know a lot. They had also been the first to reach Yamana land. Thus it was incumbent upon them to produce and design the first weapons and tools in such a way that the true Yamana were able to employ them with success. But still their sister, clever Yoálox-tárnuxipa, surpassed by far her two able brothers by her wise judgment and prudence. She exerted considerable influence on everybody. She gave instructions to the rest of the women, all of whom willingly complied. The women, in turn, ordered their husbands about and the men obliged them in every way. The sister of the two Yoálox was really extraordinarily clever; she surpassed all people in wise insight, shrewdness, and talent. Whenever it seemed appropriate she would help her two brothers and all the women with their work. Then everybody was very successful, always reaping rich returns in their enterprises.</p>
<p>One day the Yoálox brothers were making a yékuš. But although they were skillful craftsmen and worked hard all day, the arrowhead would not turn out quite right. They had provided it with good, sharp edges, but were unable to fasten the point securely to the shaft. To accomplish tying the point firmly to the shaft was obviously essential if the arrow was to be of any use at all. But the two Yoálox had rounded the lower edge of the arrowhead so that the threads for attaching it found no secure hold nor did the point find enough support in the narrow notch at the upper end of the shaft. An arrow like this was good for nothing. The brothers labored hard trying again and again, and in every way possible, to mount the arrowhead securely onto the shaft. They had already made and tested a good number of points but none of them turned out to their satisfaction. The points came off very easily precisely because this lower end was rounded. Discontented they gathered the many arrowheads into a small basket and hung it up in their hut.</p>
<p><pb n="37"/>One day the two Yoálox went out hunting for some meat. When they had gone a good distance away from their hut Yoálox-tárnuxipa took down the small basket with the arrowheads. It had not escaped her how utterly unsuccessful her two brothers had been. She emptied all the arrowheads on the ground in front of her. Then, picking them up one after another, she started working them over and perfecting them so that they would become usable. On the lower edge she fashioned a plug-shaped peg, providing it with a shallow notch on both sides so that the binding could not slip off. In this fashion she improved each of the arrowheads, put them all back into the little basket, and returned it to its place. In the evening the two brothers came home; but the woman did not reveal to them that she had perfected all the arrowheads herself.</p>
<p>The next day the two Yoálox wanted to resume their work on the arrowheads and see how they could be fastened firmly to the shaft and whether they were usable. Sulky and annoyed, they took down the basket and emptied it on the ground. They were very surprised to see that the points had been worked over, for each now came with a well-defined and plug-shaped peg at the base. They marveled at this change. They began testing them at once; they placed an arrowhead into the notch at the upper end of the shaft and wound fine tendons around the peg. And indeed, the point stuck firmly to the shaft and no longer fell off. Finally the arrow was usable.</p>
<p>Now the elder Yoálox exclaimed: "Who could have reworked these arrowheads, who could have made them usable?" To this the younger Yoálox responded: "Only our sister could have accomplished this; is she not much more capable and skillful than we are? She can do anything. Nobody but she could have improved these arrowheads and made them usable!" The elder Yoálox agreed with his brother: "Certainly, that's the way it is," he said. "Our sister outdoes us both in cleverness and skill. From now on we shall give her all our tools so that she may help us [in making and perfecting them]!" For a long time the two Yoálox continued to be very happy over these useful arrow points.</p>
</body>