<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB_XML/main/Schema/FFDB_mini.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB_XML/main/Schema/FFDB_mini.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<body>
<head>NSA010292</head>
<p>Once there was a man sitting on the beach while his wife was gathering mussels. She saw smoke rising nearby and asked her husband: "Who can that be who is coming here?" The man answered: "That has to be the wasénim, for they are very clumsy, deformed paunch-bellies!" Meanwhile these people<note>The tufted cormorant, Phalacrocorax gaimardi, common species in this area.</note> had gotten close enough to overhear quite clearly that man's contemptuous remark.</p>
<p>The wasénim got out of their canoes and right away started to build a hut. In the course of this they tried to strike up a conversation with the man asking him for fire. Their behavior was decidely peculiar. Then the man realized that the wasénim must have overheard his contemptuous comment. So he invited them in a friendly manner: "Come into my hut and make yourselves at home; there is room enough!" But the wasénim replied in a waspish tone: "We can't possibly accept your invitation. After all, we're deformed paunch-bellies and incapable of walking through the entrance!" Now the man was certain, and very courteously gave them the desired fire. The wasénim settled down in their own hut. They began discussing how they could make a fool of that man and take revenge on him who had insulted them gravely and behaved so contemptuously toward them.</p>
<p>Soon night fell. Now the wasénim asked the man: "Do you feel like accompanying us to fish and hunt? The weather is very favorable!" They intended to play a good practical joke on him. The man found himself more or less compelled to agree; his wife, the éetexkípa,<note>The other species of native cormorant, Phalacrocorax magellanicus.</note> <pb n="65"/>belonged to the family of the wasénim, and for this reason alone he was not free to refuse the invitation. So all of them got into the canoe of the wasénim. In the stern sat the éetexkípa; she paddled and steered the boat. They went far out. Finally they reached an island where they disembarked and killed many sea lions and collected large amounts of fish. They loaded the catch into their canoe.</p>
<p>The éetexkípa was very shrewd and cunning; besides, the wasénim had secretly given her some advance instructions.<note>Here it is made clear that a woman unhesitatingly sticks by her family, even against her husband if he has offended her honor.</note> She was still sitting in the stern of the canoe, paddling and steering it such that the current could not pull it out from shore. When the bulk of the catch had been loaded on board she continued to move her paddle as though to keep the canoe near shore. But that was deliberately deceitful. She actually let the canoe slowly drift farther and farther away from the beach. All the while the wasénim were bringing the last part of their catch from the island to the canoe. The latter was now floating far away from the island but the wasénim were flying back and forth, bringing meat and leaving again. The éetexkípa was still sitting in the stern paddling with preplanned deceitfulness.</p>
<p>The husband had remained on the island. He could not fly. When the last wasénim was about to leave the island to get into the canoe he asked the man: "Well, aren't you thinking of coming with us? All the men have already gotten in. Take a long jump and you'll be in the canoe!" Not until then did the man realize that the canoe had gone far out. Disappointedly he said: "I can't jump all the way there; it's too far for me." The wasénim encouraged him: "Don't you see how your wife is paddling all the time? She can't possibly bring the canoe closer to you! All right, then you have to stay here!" With a long jump the last wasénim sprang into the canoe. The man was unable to follow, because the canoe had gone too far out. All the wasénim laughed very loudly and maliciously shouted over to the man on the island: "Well, are you convinced now that we are no clumsy paunch-bellies? Just look at us: all of us have reached the canoe with one jump! But you may indeed have to stay behind over there." Then they paddled away and did not even look back.</p>
<p>Thus the man sat all alone on the island and found himself in a great dilemma. Yet he knew how to get out of it. The next morning he looked for a thick cudgel and with it killed a big male sea lion. He made a little cut in the stomach, and through this small opening he took out all the meat and fat. The skin he placed in such a way that it quickly dried. <pb n="66"/>Then he sewed up all the openings and inflated the entire skin very tightly. He pushed it into the water where it stayed afloat. So he mounted it and finally, after a good while, reached the place where his hut stood. Those wasénim had surely taken revenge on the man who had ridiculed them so.</p>
</body>