<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB_XML/main/Schema/FFDB_mini.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB_XML/main/Schema/FFDB_mini.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<body>
<head>NSA010298</head>
<p>A brother had fallen in love with his own sister.<note>Here, too, males and females of the large woodpecker species Ipocrantor magellanicus are meant.</note> He therefore tried in every way possible to meet and sleep with her. His sister had long noticed his intention. She avoided him every time for she did not want to have forbidden intercourse with him. Yet she was of two minds, half willing, half unwilling. The brother considered what pretext to use to lure her out of the hut.</p>
<p>One day he discovered big berries<note>The well-liked fruits of Pernettya mucronata (Gusinde 1937:121, fig. 12).</note> in a clearing in the forest. A sly thought occurred to him. He said to himself: "I shall tell my sister now that I have found big berries here. After that I'm sure she'll come here." He promptly ran back to the hut and told his sister: "I have found big berries in a certain place in the forest; you should go there and get them!" The girl took her basket and hurried into the woods.</p>
<p>Without anybody noticing it the brother quickly sneaked after her. He hid in a place where his sister had to pass. Once she had gotten close enough he embraced her. Then both lay down and yielded to their desire. But when they wanted to get up after the wicked thing they had done, they found themselves turned into birds. Both were all black. In addition, the brother has since had a bright red head;<note>This clearly refers to the dimorphism between male and female, already alluded to on p. 79 n. 18.</note> it was those big, <pb n="81"/>red berries that he pointed out to his sister in order to do bad things with her.<note>This tale is obviously a variant of the preceding one. Both set out to explain the strikingly close and enduring relationship of the monogamous woodpecker couple. The second version is a more substantive and perfect narrative, while the first lays greater stress on the moral gravity of incest.</note></p>
</body>