<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB_XML/main/Schema/FFDB_mini.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB_XML/main/Schema/FFDB_mini.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<body>
<head>NSA010300</head>
<p>One day the big gerfalcon<note>Polyborus tharus. This big bird of prey is common in southern Chile and Argentina where it is generally known as traro or carancho.</note> went out to the rocks in the open sea. He wanted to kill sea lions there. Many other men accompanied him. All were married but they left their wives at home and set off without them. They had a long way to go and the weather was very bad. After several days they finally reached the rocky islands where they killed many sea lions. They were very happy over this. Then they sat down to rest, for they were exhausted. Soon one after the other fell asleep, until eventually only two men who were talking to each other remained awake. The gerfalcon had already lain down. But he was only pretending to be asleep; he just couldn't fall asleep.</p>
<p>The two men were sitting very close to the gerfalcon. One of them said quietly to the other: "Listen: next to us here lies Ketéla. Do you know his pretty wife, Lúškipa? Well, I'll let you in on something: I have long been having relations with her secretly. She's really a beautiful woman." The other one at once admonished him: "But don't talk about it here. After all, Ketéla is lying next to us; he might easily hear us talking!" The first man replied: "Well, now, don't worry about that! So far as I can see Ketéla is already fast asleep; he can't hear what we're whispering about. This encouraged the other man and he admitted: "Now I want to reveal something to you, too. I have also been having secret relations with beautiful Lúškipa for quite some time. I have already met her secretly many times. She is most certainly a delightful woman!" In this way the two men were confiding in each other, the one telling the other about his secret doings with the gerfalcon's beautiful wife. The gerfalcon, however, was still acting as though fast asleep. Therefore he heard their words very well.</p>
<p>The next morning the men loaded all the sea lions they had killed into their canoes and returned to where their families were waiting. When they arrived, every man went to his own hut. Ketéla, however, did not go to his hut where his wife was waiting but rather into that of one of his relatives. He did send a piece of meat to his wife in the hut, but without any greeting. She found it very strange that her husband did not come to the hut himself and had given her nothing but one piece of meat. Finally she realized what was going on. She said to herself: "My husband has probably heard what I secretly do with other men and with whom I've been sleeping. Surely that's why he comes to the hut no longer and sends me nothing but a small piece of meat!" <pb n="87"/>Lúškipa was completely at a loss and did not know what to do. She was very sad at having to sit there alone. After a while she left her hut and ran away. She ran down to the beach intending to run along the shore until she met her father, old Dášlux.<note>Diomedea melanophrys, the large albatross (Gusinde 1937:43).</note></p>
<p>Lúškipa ran along the beach for a long time until she finally saw a canoe on the water. She waved to it to come closer. She had to signal for a long time, but at last the canoe changed course and turned to where Lúškipa was waiting on the shore.</p>
<p>Indeed, it was her father who was sitting in the canoe. She was very happy that she had finally reached him. She immediately told her father everything and explained why she had run away looking for him.</p>
<p>Soon Ketéla noticed that his wife had disappeared from their hut. That made him very sad. But he composed himself and quickly ran after her; he wanted to find her and bring her home again. He set off in the same direction she had taken. Finally he came close to the place where she was still sitting with her father. But when those two saw Ketéla approaching they quickly got into their canoe and left. Ketéla had come on foot, so he could not follow them far running along the beach. Angry and sad, he had to watch Lúškipa go farther and farther away with her father. He followed them with his eyes for a long time.</p>
<p>In his anguish he looked for a bird's egg. He threw it on the ground, breaking it; he wanted to ensure himself good luck. Promptly he summoned all the winds, the wind from the east and the wind from the west, the wind from the south and the wind from the north. All four winds came at once and they blew powerfully, each one from its direction. The canoe in which Lúškipa and her father were sitting no longer moved from its spot, for the winds were blowing very strongly from all sides. Thus the canoe now sat in the middle of the wide waterway unable to continue. That was Ketéla's intention. Not until the following day was it completely calm again, and then the two paddled off in their canoe. They traveled quickly, for they were paddling with all their strength. At last they reached their hut. There the old man and his daughter got out. From then on beautiful Lúškipa remained with her father forever.</p>
<p>Sadly Ketéla went back to his people's camp. He went into his hut and sat down by the fire. But now he was all alone. He sat there sorrowfully for a long time; he cried long and loud. A woman came by his hut and heard his lament. She asked: "Why are you crying so much?" Ketéla answered: "Oh, the wind blew some dirt into my eyes and it hurts a lot. That's why I'm losing so many tears!" But actually <pb n="88"/>he was crying over the loss of his beautiful wife. So long and so much did he cry that even today his eyes are still very red<note>This coloration of the eyes, which frequently appear to be weeping, is very striking in the large gerfalcon, Polyborus tharus.</note> from the many, many tears he has shed over beautiful Lúškipa, and he still continues to cry over her.</p>
</body>