<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB_XML/main/Schema/FFDB_mini.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB_XML/main/Schema/FFDB_mini.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<body>
<head>NSA010323</head>
<p>Once Yookalía<note>The sparrow hawk, Milvago chimango.</note> came to a camp where he met a beautiful girl. He liked her very much, so he stayed. But he himself was not popular and had only a few friends among those people. Eventually he fell deeply in love with the girl. He frequently went to her hut to offer his love, but to no avail. Still he kept coming to her hut, and finally she let herself be persuaded and promised to become his wife. Yookalía was extremely happy over this and both now lived together. But one night when he <pb n="160"/>came quietly to her bed and revealed his intention to sleep with her, the girl energetically pushed him back and would have nothing to do with him any more. That made him very sad, for he realized now that the girl no longer wanted to be his wife. He complained to the other people but they laughed at him. He simply had no friends there; nobody knew him well enough. Whenever they had a chance these people would always make fun of him, even the girl he loved.</p>
<p>The men often went out to hunt guanacos but they never took Yookalía along. Every time they killed a guanaco they filled a twisted piece of gut with its blood and made a sausage which they brought back to the hut. But for Yookalía they made another sausage, for they wanted to make fun of him. With a pointed stick they poked around in their noses until blood flowed; this blood they gathered up in a piece of gut and prepared a kéti [a special kind of sausage]. This sausage they brought back to the hut to give to Yookalía. He roasted it over the fire and ate it. The others looked on and secretly laughed. The men did not give Yookalía anything else to eat; therefore he kept growing paler and thinner. Although he asked for something different, the people gave him nothing else, and when he asked for more of the same, they did not give him any.</p>
<p>Yookalía had now grown very weak and thin indeed. One day the people returned from hunting and, as usual, gave him the blood sausage. Since he was very hungry he ate it, and the others secretly laughed. But two good friends that he now had among the women finally felt sorry for him. They told Yookalía: "Listen, what you're eating is a sausage made of human blood. The people made this kind of sausage for you with blood from their noses!" He became furious, threw the remainder away, and would no longer eat anything.</p>
<p>Since the people had treated him so badly he decided to leave their camp. He had very good arrows and a beautiful bow. Without anybody noticing he pushed his weapons outside the hut from within. Then he told his two good friends: "Now paint me nicely because I'm returning to my parents! The people here don't like me. But they'll get their punishment. You two will be rewarded for having treated me well." The two women painted him beautifully. Unobtrusively he took his weapons which he had earlier pushed out of the hut and, before anyone realized it, he had left.</p>
<p>He went in the direction of his father's place. But he had to go past the hut of a bad, evil-minded woman. As Yookalía came closer the woman wanted to kill him. But the younger Yoálox who goes around everywhere hid Yookalía and he was saved. He continued on. Wherever he spent the night he made a big fire to warm himself. That way all the places he had passed were marked.</p>
<p><pb n="161"/>When he was close to his father's hut his younger brother, who was standing by the entrance, saw him. Instantly he called into the hut: "Far in the distance there I see a man; I'm sure it is my brother!" To this the mother said: "That man in the distance can't possibly be your brother. Surely he died long ago. I haven't heard from him in a long time." Gradually the man came closer and closer; he was walking slowly as he was very weak and worn out. But when he entered the hut his mother recognized him at once and was happy that he had come. Since he was so pale and thin his mother asked him: "Why are you so pale and so thin?" He replied: "Those people there treated me very badly; even my bride made a fool of me. They only fed me sausages of human blood, nothing else. Therefore I grew thinner and thinner, and finally I fled." Sympathetically the mother asked: "But how was this possible?" He replied: "Two good friends among the women told me everything. Then I wouldn't eat anything any more and left."</p>
<p>The father sat on his bed and heard everything. He became very indignant that those people had treated his son so badly. Then he lay down and soon fell asleep. In his dream he wanted to kill a whale, let it wash ashore, and then spoil its meat so that everyone who had treated his son badly would be punished. Now he was dreaming, and he killed a big whale in his dream. Then he let it be stranded near the camp of those people; in his dream he recognized all those who had mistreated his son. Finally he placed himself personally inside the whale. He wanted to watch those who came and to see what pieces each would receive. Now at last would be punished all those who had given his son the sausage made of human blood.</p>
<p>The next morning a man from that camp saw the big whale lying on the beach. He quickly called the people. They came hurrying. Each got a big piece of blubber; all ate and were very contented. Yookalía's bride, too, got her piece; his two good friends also got their pieces, and all were very contented. But the old yékamuš, Yookalía's father, who was sitting inside the whale, saw exactly which piece of blubber was given to whom. When all the people had eaten plenty he suddenly transformed all the consumed pieces of blubber except for those that had been eaten by Yookalía's two friends. Suddenly the pieces of blubber began to move in everyone's stomach as though they were coming alive again. They were strongly pulled toward the place where the whale was lying; and along with them they were also pulling the bride and all those people who had given Yookalía human blood. The individual pieces assembled themselves perfectly on their own accord. The whale came alive again and swam off with the people who had remained stuck to it. Only Yookalía's two good friends were spared.</p>
<p><pb n="162"/>Even today one can still see all those people sticking to the whale's back.<note>This refers to the many parasites, above all the common Balanus psittacus (Gusinde 1937:577, 591), with which every older whale appears to be covered.</note> That is how the old yékamuš avenged his son, Yookalía, because those people had given him sausages of human blood.<note>This story shows close similarities to two Selknam stories, entitled "The Revenge of Elankáiyink" (Gusinde 1931:642; Wilbert 1975:92) and "How Hačámšes Took Revenge" (Wilbert 1975:98).</note></p>
</body>