<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB_XML/main/Schema/FFDB_mini.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB_XML/main/Schema/FFDB_mini.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<body>
<head>NSA010291</head>
<p><note>See also Koppers 1924:194-197.</note></p>
<p>The éetex<note>The Magellanic cormorant, Phalacrocorax magellanicus (Gusinde 1937:1189, fig. 91).</note> was always very selfish. One day he found a small spring that contained some water. It had not rained for a long time, so that all the people were terribly thirsty. But the éetex kept the small hole hidden and only went there in secret, unwilling to share the water with the others.</p>
<p>The wasénim<note>The well-known tufted cormorant, Phalacrocorax gaimardi.</note> suffered immensely from thirst. He searched everywhere for water but could not find any. The éetex appeared very happy and contented; after all, he did not have to go thirsty. The wasénim, however, seemed sad and depressed. Despite anxious searching he had failed to find any water and was extremely thirsty. One day he asked the éetex: "How can you be so cheerful? It seems to me you don't feel any thirst at all!" The éetex answered: "I just open my mouth when it rains; then several raindrops fall in and that's enough for me." But the wasénim was cunning enough not to trust the éetex completely. He suspected that he had a spring somewhere from which he alone was drinking. Therefore he said to himself with great determination: "Some time I'm going to follow that éetex!"</p>
<p>He promptly summoned several other wasénim and together they waited for the éetex in a hiding place. Soon the latter and five other éetex came passing by. Slowly and carefully the éetex led the way for his companions, looking back anxiously with every step they took. The wasénim followed them with utmost caution. Whenever the éetex <pb n="63"/>In this way all of them slowly advanced, until finally the éetex reached the place where the little spring was. Once more they looked around and then quickly bent down to drink with great satisfaction. This, too, the wasénim were able to see. Swiftly but silently they proceeded. Coming from behind they threw themselves over the éetex who were standing far below at the edge of the small hole. They gave them such a hard push that they slid even farther down. Then the wasénim themselves began to drink. They drank for a long time, finishing all the water. At last they felt their great thirst quenched and were very content.</p>
<p>Therefore even nowadays the éetex calls "e, e, e" in a loud voice, just as he did in ancient times. His throat has always remained moist, for he had found a well to drink from and that way he did not have to go thirsty. But the wasénim still calls "eh, eh, eh" from a hoarse and empty throat, just as he used to do. At that time he could not find any water, and therefore his throat dried up completely. And on all cliffs one can see the two types of bird distributed in such a way that the éetex inhabit the lower surfaces and projections while the wasénim have the holes located farther up. On that occasion the wasénim had given the éetex such a strong push that the latter slid down forever. To this day the éetex looks back all the time, exactly as when he clandestinely went to his little well. He is still afraid of being watched and secretly followed.</p>
</body>