<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB_XML/main/Schema/FFDB_mini.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB_XML/main/Schema/FFDB_mini.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<body>
<head>NSA010335</head>
<p><note>See also Martial 1882-1883:214.</note></p>
<p>Up in the north of the Isla Grande and also on the large, beautiful plain of Yaiyióxan<note>This is the name for the level area surrounding Bahía Thetis.</note> the women were the first to perform the kína. At that time women were in sole control: they commanded the men, who were subordinate, just as today the women obey the men. Also, the men sat behind in the stern of the canoe and the women sat up front in the bow. The men did all the domestic chores according to the instructions of the women: they looked after the children, kept the fire going, cleaned the skins. That is the way it was to remain forever. For that purpose the women invented the Big Hut and everything that goes on inside it. They told the men: "We are looking for Tánuwa! Maybe we'll be able to find her; maybe she'll come out of the earth and enter the Big Hut!" The men believed this. They had to move on every time the women broke camp.</p>
<p>But they did not find Tánuwa in that region, and so they moved to another place, traveling along the north coast of the Isla Grande as far as the northeastern tip. Whenever they stopped to rest they built the kína-hut and performed again. From there they wandered south along the east coast of the Isla Grande. Wherever they performed, a large, level plain was formed. They searched every place for evil, powerful Tánuwa, continuing south until they were near Cabo San Pablo. From here on they no longer followed the coast, and this is why even today one finds only forested, mountainous country south of this cape. The women then took a southwesterly direction, crossed the mountain range, and on the south coast of Isla Grande reached the Beagle Channel near Puerto Harberton. From here they moved west. Wherever they built their kína-hut and performed, as for example at Puerto Brown, the surface of the earth changed, and level, open country was formed. They wandered along the [north] coast of the Beagle Channel continuing westward until they finally came to Yáiaašága.<note>Today generally called "Boca del infierno," doubtless derived from that myth. This place is located on the peninsula that extends southward into Bahía Ušuáia.</note> Here they performed their kína for a long time. The women came out of the Big Hut, alone or in groups, with their bodies completely painted and wearing hílix [masks] over their heads. A yékamuš would call to the men: "That is Súna-yáka!" or "That is Wasénim-yáka!" And many more spirits came out. The men believed that this was really the case. But in actual fact it was the women who had painted themselves and concealed their faces with masks so that no man could recognize them.</p>
<p><pb n="187"/>In spite of much performing and searching the women were unable to find Tánuwa and get her to come out of the earth. So they decided to travel no farther and to stay here in Yáiaašága. This area is very nice and level. They liked it very much and said: "This is where we'll stay! Now we'll deceive the men and tell them: 'We have found Tánuwa; she came out of the ground just now and is with us in the Big Hut!' " Promptly the women rolled a few dry skins into a thick roll and began thrashing the ground with it until it rang. They screamed, shouted, and cried as though frightened to death. The men heard them, ran into their huts, and hid there filled with fear. They whispered quietly to one another: "Indeed, our wives have now discovered Tánuwa! For they never screamed so long and so loud when the spirits appeared." When the terrible screaming began and the earth thundered the men said to themselves with great conviction: "That must be Tánuwa coming out of the earth. The women have found her after all!" The women continued to perform there in Yáiaašága. The men were kept in fear and subjugation, and continued to do all the chores assigned them by the women.</p>
<p>Lem, the sun-man, was an excellent hunter. He was always sent out to hunt, and he brought back plenty of game. All those women in the kína-hut needed a lot of meat. One day while out hunting Lem killed a big guanaco<note>It should be pointed out that in the central part of the Vamana territory guanacos are very rare and are hardly ever hunted by the Indians.</note> which he threw over his shoulder. Walking toward the camp he went past a lagoon and heard the voices of two girls. He became curious and said to himself: "What can these two be doing here?" He quietly sneaked up, and, hidden in the bushes, saw the two girls washing off the paint in which the "spirits" were supposed to appear. In doing so they kept practicing how to imitate the voices and the movements of his two daughters [Lem's daughters<note>Old Whaits only mentioned "a daughter of the sun-man" at this point.</note>], for the latter played an important part in the kína-hut. The girls were saying: "We want to practice well, so that we can act exactly like Lem's daughter. Then we'll help her sing, and deceive the men with her." They continued to practice while talking about the activities of the women in the kína-hut.</p>
<p>Suddenly Lem jumped out of his hiding place and stood right in front of the girls to block their escape. Very sternly he snapped at them: "What are you doing here?" Frightened, they fell silent. Then he ordered them: "You have to tell me everything - what you are doing here, what you were talking about, and what takes place in the kína-hut. I know much already, for I was listening to you." Then the girls <pb n="188"/>blushed with shame and broke out in a cold sweat. Finally they told Lem everything, confessing: "It is the women themselves who paint their bodies and put on masks; then they come out of the house and show themselves to the men. There are no others [spirits] there. It is the women themselves who scream and yell to frighten the men; Tánuwa doesn't do these things." The girls gave him still other information. Then Lem said: "In return for this I'll give you some advice: stay here at the lagoon and don't go back either to the camp or to the kína-hut, for something bad is going to happen now!" So the two girls stayed and eventually changed into little ducks.<note>As long ago as January 1920 old Whaits told me this part in a somewhat different version: The sun-man was an excellent hunter. Although he always brought back much game from the hunt, there was soon a shortage of meat again, and thus he had to go hunting constantly. The reason was that his meat was stolen by the women. One day as he was walking toward the camp carrying a heavy guanaco he happened past a lagoon where two girls were bathing. Without being seen he sneaked up and listened to their conversation. Then he heard them saying: "Lem is always bringing back much meat from the hunt. Today he is on his way home again, and surely he won't return empty-handed. But the clever women steal all the meat from him and carry it to the kína-hut where all of them eat it together, which Lem doesn't know." When the sun-man suddenly stepped out of his hiding place the girls caught sight of him and fearfully ducked below the surface of the water. But he called to them: "I've already seen you and recognized you; come on out!" Fearfully they approached. Lem told them: "What are you talking about here? I was listening to you!" They stammered: "We only said: 'Lem is always bringing home much meat, but there it is stolen from him and therefore he has to go hunting again every day!' " Lem now ordered them: "Since you know who is stealing my meat you have to tell me who they are!" Trembling, the girls revealed to him: "All the women who gather in the kína-hut steal the meat you bring, and eat it. That's why they stay so long in the kína-hut playing and frightening the men!" On Lem's advice the two girls who had revealed the secret to him remained in the lagoon. They turned into ducks, and are very timid.</note></p>
<p>Angrily Lem picked up his guanaco again and set out toward camp, all the while considering how to take revenge on the women. When he reached his hut he threw the guanaco to the ground and said fretfully: "So that's why I'm dragging all that game home every day, so that my daughters can make fun of me and deceive us men! They take away our meat as though it were for Tánuwa, and then proceed to eat it themselves in the kína-hut!" All the women who were standing near his hut listened in surprise and wondered: "What has happened? What is Lem saying? Why is he so furious?"</p>
<p>Téšurkipa<note>Today a type of sparrow with yellow feathers, rarely seen there.</note> happened to be sitting nearby, working on a harpoon point. Hearing Lem's excited words she said to herself: "Somebody must have told him about the activities of the women! Perhaps he eavesdropped on the girls who went to the lagoon to wash." She blushed with shame, for she presumed that the deceit of the women had been revealed. Then she thought: "How can I silence Lem so that he <pb n="189"/>keeps quiet and the other men don't find out?" There were many men lying in the hut in front of which the woman was sitting, and although covered up they were awake. She alone was sitting up, for after all she did not have to crawl under cover.<note>During the Kalampáša-play the people in the camp had to gather in a big dwelling hut, if possible, and here await the visit of the serpent Kalampáša. This event has already been described in Gusinde 1937:1330.</note> When Lem entered the hut the woman spoke to him in words intended to gloss over everything and make him keep silent: "We women gave the men a terrible fright just now! We all came into the hut and the men immediately crawled under the covers, thinking that we were Kalampáša." She said this in order to embarrass Lem and distract him, so that he would say nothing further and to keep the men from finding out anything.</p>
<p>Then she ran at once to the kína-hut and told the women: "Lem knows everything that goes on here!" The women became very upset at these words. They stood up, screamed loudly, painted themselves, put on masks, and went again to the hut in which all the men had gathered, intending to really frighten them now. But this time several men, without being seen, peeped out from under the furs with which they were covered, saying: "Now we won't let ourselves be scared; we'll watch closely to see if it really is our wives who're coming!" Keeping their hands over their faces they peeked through their fingers. While the women were dancing and screaming, sometimes even right into the ears of the men, the latter were watching attentively but remaining completely motionless. When after a long spell of dancing the women departed the men threw aside their covers again and said to one another: "That person was my daughter. - That one was your wife. -  That one was my wife; I recognized her. So then it wasn't Kalampáša but only our women!" Thus the deception of the women was revealed. Lem told the men in detail what he had seen and heard by the lagoon. Now the men wanted to confirm this by getting more information, and they debated what to do. Immediately they sent the fastest man among them to run after the women. He ran after them and dashed into the Big Hut: the women were sitting around the fire and each had leaned her mask against the wall behind her, so that the little man could clearly recognize the face of each and every one of them. His name was Šalalakína; today he is a little bird.<note>This timid, nimble bird lives in swampy regions. It has chocolate-covered feathers and a beautiful voice.</note> He slipped into the Big Hut and went around behind the backs of the women who were squatting there. He pushed over all the masks in the process and escaped on the other side of the wide entrance. Seeing this the women guessed that a fast runner among the men must have run through there, for how else could <pb n="190"/>all the masks have fallen! They gnashed their teeth in shame and anger, and gave loud screams. Meanwhile little Šalalakína was telling the men: "I sneaked into the hut and ran quickly from one side to the other, pushing over all the masks. But I didn't see Tánuwa. Only women are sitting there in the Big Hut." The men were listening.</p>
<p>They believed that they had to get even more evidence, however, for they wanted to know whether the women were deceiving them with all their talk about Tánuwa. Therefore they now sent off this man, now that one, who could run particularly fast, first the smaller ones, then the bigger. Each sneaked in on one side, dashed through, and escaped on the other. Soon the women noticed this and picked up their bows and arrows. After each man who ran through the hut and pushed over their masks they shot an arrow which stuck in his backside and became a tail. Particularly easy targets were the heavy animals [which were men at that time], and that is why they have a tail to this day. The women threw a harpoon after the otter, and for that reason it has a wide tail to this day. After the fox they threw an uškútta-shrub<note>This is the winter pepper tree, Drimys winteri (Gusinde 1937:28).</note> that was lying there, with all its leaves and twigs; it stuck in his backside and that is why the fox has a bushy tail. This way each of the men who ran through the Big Hut was driven out by the women.</p>
<p>Finally when there were no more fast runners among the men they rested. Then they armed themselves with clubs and slings, with harpoons and spears, with bows and arrows, and marched on the Big Hut. The women were overcome with terrible fear. But the men stormed forward and a raging battle began, the men falling furiously on the women. Only two of the latter were able to escape unharmed; all the others were badly beaten and turned into animals, and one can tell from all of them that they received some hard blows on that occasion. During the battle Lem poured masses of water on the kína-hut to put out the fire, for it had started to burn. He poured so much water that it became a mighty wave. This wave went far out into the ocean, taking with it the big sea animals, for there is no room for them on land [no way for them to move around]. Even today one sees this wave: it is the heavy surf breaking against the high outlying rocks. With his sling Lem threw a large bucket [túku] filled to the brim with water into the fire so that a strong hissing sound was heard. This sound, too, went out into the ocean, and can be heard even today through the mighty rumble of the waves.</p>
<p>All the women were killed or transformed; some fled; only the small children were unharmed. Soon after this furious battle Lem the <pb n="191"/>sun-man went up to the sky, and so did his brother Akáinix, the rainbow, and the latter's wife Hánuxa, the moon-woman. Since that time the men alone perform in the kína-hut, in the same tradition and manner as did the women before them.</p>
</body>