<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB_XML/main/Schema/FFDB_mini.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/KatjaMellmann/FFDB_XML/main/Schema/FFDB_mini.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<body>
<head>NSA010296</head>
<p>Although little detehúrux was still very young<note>In the Cape Horn area there are two species of woodpecker. This myth is dedicated to the smaller of the two, Dendrocopus lignarius (Gusinde 1937:42).</note> he had already fallen in love, and with his own mother, at that. She was always carrying her <pb n="76"/>little son around with her. For that purpose she had made a bag from pieces of hide; she put the little detehúrux into it and constantly carried him around on her back. She never took the little boy out of the bag, and whenever she left her hut she slung the bag on her back. That way the small boy was never without his mother.</p>
<p>This woman went frequently into the forest. She told the people: "I find the ésef<note>Mushroom; this general term is used for all stages of growth of the species Cyttaria darwinii (Gusinde 1937:554).</note> so delicious that I always have to go out into the forest to collect a lot of these mushrooms." But she always went alone, taking only her son along in the bag. As soon as she found a hidden place in the forest she stopped. Her little son became a full-grown man and quickly left the sack in which he had been sitting. Without delay he climbed up into the trees and picked ésef. Then he threw many of them down to the woman below who gathered them up. After some time he called to his mother from up there: "Lie down on the ground and part your legs as far as you can; I want to throw ésef into your vagina!" The woman immediately lay down on the ground with great pleasure, and with her legs stretched far apart she opened her vagina very wide. The son hit his mother's vagina with the ésef thrown from the tree, which was a very great pleasure for both of them. After playing like this for a rather long time the son climbed down from the tree. Then he lay down on his mother and she received him with great pleasure, for his penis was extremely large.</p>
<p>After they had spent a long time doing this they finally got up. The son got into the bag, became smaller and smaller, until he had become an infant again. The mother hurried back to the hut with him. Again they had returned with a large amount of ésef. These they distributed among the other women; all ate a lot and appeared very content. The mother and her son went often to the forest, but always alone, and every time they played around in this wicked manner.</p>
<p>The other women were mystified and asked the woman: "How do you manage to gather that many ésef in so short a time? You always bring a large amount to the camp." Calmly the woman replied: "I always go out alone into the forest and climb up into the trees to quickly pick a lot of ésef." From then on the other women did exactly as that mother had told them; but still they were unable to gather that many ésef in so short a time.</p>
<p>Finally one day several women followed the mother unnoticed as she again disappeared alone into the forest. As usual, she was carrying only <pb n="77"/>her son in the bag. When the two had gone far into the forest the astonished women saw how the little son quickly left the bag and became a full-grown man. He promptly climbed up into the trees and rapidly broke off a large number of ésef. Below, the mother hastened to gather up the ésef. Then after a while the son again called to her from above: "Lie down on the ground and part your legs as far as you can, I want to throw ésef into your vagina!" The woman immediately lay down on the ground with great pleasure, and with her legs stretched far apart she opened her vagina very wide. The son hit his mother's vagina with the ésef thrown from the tree, which was a great pleasure for both of them. After playing like this for a rather long time the son climbed down from the tree. Then he lay down on his mother and she received him with great pleasure, for his penis was extremely large.</p>
<p>The women saw and heard all this from their hiding place and were horrified. Unnoticed, they rushed back to their huts and soon revealed to the husband of the woman that the two of them, the mother and the son, would go off together and yield to incestuous pleasure. He seemed very surprised, for until then he had believed his son to be very small still. Indeed his mother always carried him in the bag on her back without ever letting him out; the father had so far only seen his face. In fact, the mother had never allowed the little boy to leave the bag if another person was in the hut. She carried the bag firmly strapped to her back. For she said to herself: "If I let my son out of the bag his father will notice at once that his penis is very long. In view of this he will start to suspect that he has intercourse with a woman!" Thus she kept the son always tied up in the bag and carried him constantly around with her. She did not let him out at night either, because he had nothing with which to cover his body.</p>
<p>The husband now considered what those women had revealed to him. He took a knife and made it sharp enough to cut leather. The following day his wife hurried again into the forest and did not return until evening. As usual she was carrying her little son in the bag on her back. She brought very many ésef. Then he spoke to her in a friendly tone: "Why do you never put down the bag with the little boy? After all, that load must be very heavy if you carry it around with you all day." She replied curtly, fending him off: "Our little son is still very small, so that I have to protect him extra carefully! Actually I don't notice any burden at all; our boy is still very small, you know." But the husband quickly replied: "Do rest a little now and trust me with the bag!" In saying this he took his sharp knife and severed the leather straps by which the bag hung from his wife's back. At once the bag <pb n="78"/>dropped down and tore apart. The little boy fell to the ground and on his back with his legs far apart. Then the father could see his son's large penis, as he was not dressed. Now he knew enough! Beside himself with horror he seized the knife he had sharpened, and cut off his son's large penis. Although much blood flowed, the furious man let him lie there. Finally the little boy became a bird. Since then he has stayed in the forest and never again returned to his parents' hut. That is the little detehúrux who even today has a powerful beak with a long, red tongue inside.<note>Although the myth is in itself obvious, its meaning is made even more explicit with these words.</note></p>
</body>